<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word in season: being the commentary of Dr. Martin Luther, on three selected Psalms: viz. the CXXIVth, CXXVth, and CXXIXth. With his commentary on some part of the fourth and fifth chapters of the First Epistle of St. Peter. Being of special use for the present times.</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R180278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578390</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578390</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172313</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88660)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2625:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word in season: being the commentary of Dr. Martin Luther, on three selected Psalms: viz. the CXXIVth, CXXVth, and CXXIXth. With his commentary on some part of the fourth and fifth chapters of the First Epistle of St. Peter. Being of special use for the present times.</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Larkin at the lower end of Broad-street, next to London-Wall.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXIV --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXV --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXIX --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, IV-V --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172313:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A word in Seaſon: BEING THE COMMENTARY OF <hi>Dr. Martin
Luther,</hi> ON Three SELECT PSALMS: <hi>VIZ.</hi> The CXXIVth, CXXVth, and
CXXIXth.</p>
            <p>WITH His Commentary on ſome part of the Fourth and Fifth
Chapters of the Firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being of ſpecial Vſe for the preſent Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES. XII. 11.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>The Words of the wiſe are goads, and as nails fastened by the
Masters of Aſſemblies, which are given from one Shepherd.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>George Larkin</hi> at the lower
End of <hi>Broad-street,</hi> next to <hi>London-Wall.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:172313:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172313:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT would be an unaccountable Preſumption for me to commend to
thy good Opinion the Author of the Commentary on the Pſalms, and that part of
St. <hi>Peters</hi> Firſt Epiſtle, preſented to thee in the following
Sheets. If thou art a <hi>Proteſtant Chriſtian,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently
acquainted with Authors, thou muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Dr. <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> a
Worthy of the Firſt Rank next the Apoſtles, if not the Firſt alſo in
that Rank; or ſtand by thy ſelf, as ſome odd ſingle Exception, from the
ſtream of thy Profeſſion. But if thou art a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and
ſo of a Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination as contradictory to it ſelf, as thy Papal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
are to Truth, Reaſon, Sence, and Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, I muſt not hope the
Authors Name (than which, to thoſe of thy Profeſſion, none is more
abhorred) will commend his Work to thy Peruſal, much leſs thy
Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces.</p>
            <p>That mighty Oppoſition which this Worthy met with <pb facs="tcp:172313:3"/>in
his Succeſsful Attempts of pulling down the Papal Power, was an Exerciſe
for ſuch a Faith and Courage as the God of all Grace had filled him withal:
And the Commentaries following expreſs as much of both, as any of his
Numerous Tracts. And this conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with the ſad Parallel of our
<hi>Preſent Confuſions,</hi> and their <hi>Cauſes,</hi> with thoſe of
his Days; Thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Remedies (animated with the ſame Spirit) are with
much reaſon propoſed for thy Support, under our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Calamities; if
not alſo, as of ſome Tendency to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Cure.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but ſuch who have not proſtituted their Souls to
their Senſuality, and their Religion to thoſe who bid moſt, and the
Church of Chriſt to the Luſts of Antichriſt, will Accept and Approve of
theſe Flowers out of <hi>Luther's</hi> Garden, as Eminently Seaſonable, and
to a Spiritual Palate, no leſs Savoury.</p>
            <p>I have no further to acquaint thee with, but that this Commentary
is according to the Engliſh Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of the Latin, Printed in the
year <hi>1615.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="Psalm 124" type="commentary">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172313:3"/>
            <head>THE COMMENTARY OF Dr. <hi>MARTIN L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THER,</hi> Upon the CXXIV
PSALM.</head>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſ. 1.</hi> If the Lord had not been on our ſide,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Pſalm is a Thankſgiving to God for his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in
preſerving his People, placed (as the ſtories do ſhew) in the midſt of
the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and Heathen People,<note place="margin">The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of
the Pſalm.</note> as a flock of Sheep in a wild Forreſt, or in reſpect of
the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as a City compared to a mighty Kingdom,<note place="margin">The
People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> as a flock of Sheep among many Wolves.</note> being
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed on every ſide with the Kings of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi>
the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> the <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> the
<hi>Moabites;</hi> whom Satan had ſtirred up with deadly hatred, to vex and
perſecute them, ſeeking by all means to root them out from the Earth, that
thereby he might utterly deface and aboliſh the Word and Worſhip of the
Lord. This danger <hi>David</hi> ſaw, and thanked God which had preſerved
his People from the rage of ſo many Lyons and Dragons, which
not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that they never ceaſed to ſeek their Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet
all that they went about was in vain. And what a miracle was this, that this
People could ſo long continue, notwithſtanding the malice and rage of ſo
many Devils? <hi>David</hi> therefore in this Pſalm exhorteth his People to
be <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172313:4"/>thankful to the Lord their God ſo mightily preſerving,
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending and delivering them from the violence of ſo many Nations and
Kingdoms, hating and perſecuting them on every ſide.</p>
               <p>Which Pſalm we alſo do ſing, not only againſt our
adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries which hate and perſecute the Word, but alſo againſt
ſpiritual Wickedneſs. For we are taught by the Goſpel that there are now
ſeven Devils which lye in wait for us, (whereas we were before in danger but
of one) which ceaſe not to ſtir up the whole World againſt us. Yea our
Caſe were more tollerable if we had but only the World, and not Satan alſo
with all his Angels and the gates of Hell, wholly bent againſt us. But yet
further to moleſt and vex us; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all theſe, we have alſo the
third Enemy, which we car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry always about with us, which we nouriſh alſo
and foſter at home with us, and even within us, the fleſh I mean, which
giveth us no reſt, but continually tempteth us to Sin, fighteth againſt
Faith, and ſtriveth in our members againſt the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch then as the Church of God is never free from theſe
dangers, let us alſo ſing to the praiſe of Chriſt this Pſalm: that he
preſerveth us his members from all theſe Enemies. For it were extream
ingratitude not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this miracle, that notwithſtanding all
theſe, the Church doth yet continue, and that there be ſome which truly
teach and confeſs Chriſt, and believe in Chriſt, thô Satan rage,
the World and falſe Brethren conſpire againſt us, and the fleſh (as an
untamed Beaſt) fight againſt the Word and Faith never ſo much. This is
the benefit then that <hi>David</hi> ſo highly extolleth, and wiſheth that
his People would underſtand and give thanks to God for the ſame.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Verſe 1.</bibl> 
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the Lord had not been on our ſide, may</hi> Iſrael
<hi>now ſay:</hi>
                  </p> 
                  <bibl>Verſe 2.</bibl> 
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the Lord had not been been on our ſide, when men roſe
up againſt us,</hi>
                  </p> 
                  <bibl>Verſe 3.</bibl> 
                  <p>
                     <hi>They had then ſwallowed us up quick when their wrath was
kindled againſt us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172313:4"/>
               <p>Here the Prophet <hi>David</hi> exhorteth the People to
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how mercifully God hath delivered them from the hands of their
Enemies, and how miraculouſly he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that Kingdom, and alſo to
praiſe God with him for the ſame. Which words are not to be reſtrained to
<hi>Davids</hi> time only. For the Heathen People had oftentimes before warred
againſt them with ſuch Force and Power as was like to the rage of moſt
huge and terrible floods of Water (whereof he ſpeaketh here) ready to
overflow them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing he mentioneth here no one kind of
deliverance, it ſeemeth that he meaneth in theſe words of Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to
ſet forth whatſoever God had done for the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and deliverance of his
People at any time before. Wherein he ſheweth (as it were in a glaſs) the
dangerous ſtate of the Church from the beginning, that the faithful may learn
to know that it hath not been preſerved by the ſtrength and policy of man,
but by the miraculous power and hand of God, and therefore in their troubles
and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould always flie to God for help and ſuccour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſignifieth the People of God. Let us
acknowledge then that there is no way for Gods People to eſcape the hands of
their Enemies, but by the help and power of God, and that he will have the
glory and praiſe thereof to be given to him alone. This praiſe can none
give unto God, but the true <hi>Iſrael,</hi> having experience both of their
own weakneſs, the force and power of their Enemies, the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers paſt, and
of the merciful help and Protection of the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 2.</hi> If the Lord had not been on our ſide,
when men roſe up againſt us.</head>
               <p>This repetition is not in vain. For whilſt we are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
our fear is without meaſure: but when it is once paſt, we imagine it to
have been leſs then it was indeed. And this is the deluſion of Satan, to
diminiſh and obſcure the Grace of God. <hi>David</hi> therefore with this
repetition ſtirreth up the People to greater thankfulneſs unto God for his
graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Deliverance and amplifieth the dangers which they had 
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172313:5"/>paſſed. Whereby we are taught how to think of our
trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and afflictions paſt, leaſt the ſence and feeling of Gods Grace
vaniſh out of our minds. And here note, how God dealeth with his People in
their diſtreſs, who ſuffereth their Enemies ſo far to prevail over
them, and deferreth his help ſo long, till it ſeem impoſſible for them
to eſcape: ſo that they are compelled to confeſs and acknowledge, that
they muſt needs have periſhed if the mighty hand of God had not delivered
them. Theſe two things then we ſee the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> here to
acknowledge: firſt, That the Lord was on their ſide, that is, ſuccoured
and delivered them; then alſo that it had not been poſſible but they
muſt utterly have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, if God had not preſerved and defended
them.</p>
               <p>By <hi>men</hi> is here underſtood whatſoever is great and
migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the world; as if he ſaid: We are counted as abjects and out
caſts of the world. The Princes, the Rulers, the Wiſe, the Rich of the
world riſe up againſt us, to deſtroy us and to root us out from the face
of the earth. If ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with how great and how many Kingdoms we are
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about, which bear a deadly hatred againſt us, we may ſeem
like to a ſilly Sheep compaſſed about with a multitude of cruel Wolves,
every moment ready to devour it. That we live in ſafety therefore, and that
our Enemies prevail not againſt us, acknowledge it to be the great mercy of
God, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which ſo miraculouſly preſerveth and defendeth
ſo ſmall a flock.</p>
               <p>In like manner we are compelled to ſay and confeſs at this
day, that if God did not miraculouſly defend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his Church, the
Power of Satan is ſo great, that one of his Angels is able in one moment to
deſtroy us all, that either teach or profeſs Chriſt, and to fill the
World with bloodſhed and ſlaughter. We ſee the Princes, the Pope, the
Prelates, the mighty and wealthy of the World, yea the whole world in a manner
bent to deſtroy us. Againſt whom what have we to defend us, but that the
Lord of Hoſts hath ſtretched out his mighty arm over us, which as a brazen
wall, defendeth us againſt all the cruel darts which both Satan and the world
do dayly caſt againſt us? That we live then, that we teach, and you hear
the word, that we <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172313:5"/>have place and liberty in the Church ſo
to do, theſe things Satan cannot abide, and therefore he raiſeth the gates
of Hell againſt us; notwithſtanding he is compelled to ſuffer all theſe
things through the power of Chriſt our King, who ſitteth at the right hand
of God; for by mans ſtrength and power theſe things could not be retained
and defended. If Satan then at any time have his will in troubling the Church,
in murthering the people of God, and ſuch like, therefore it is, becauſe
God would ſhew what Satan is able to do every moment if he were not
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by the almighty power of God, to the end that we ſhould walk in
the fear of God, and acknowledging this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable benefit, continually
pray unto God for the ſame. Let us learn then to ſing with <hi>David: If
the Lord had not been on our ſide, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe mighty hand hath
defended us, whoſe power alone hath preſerved us. And although the world
rage againſt us, though Satan vex us never ſo ſore, they cannot hurt us.
<hi>Be of good comfort</hi> (ſaith Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour) <hi>for I have
overcome the world.</hi> Again; <hi>I give unto them everlaſting life, and
none ſhall take them out of my hand.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 3.</hi> They had then ſwallowed us up quick,
when their wrath was kindled againſt us.</head>
               <p>In theſe words he expreſſeth, not only the ſtrength,
rage, and cruelty of the enemies: but alſo how weak and unable the
Iſraelites were to withſtand them. And here he uſeth a ſimilitude taken
of fierce and outragious beaſts, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty is, when they have taken
their Preys, to ſwallow them up alive. Likewiſe when we would expreſs the
cruelty or malice of any towards us, we are wont to ſay: He hateth me ſo
deadly, that he could find in his heart to eat me, or ſwallow me up quick.
The Prophet meaneth then that their enemies were ſo many and ſo mighty,
that they need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no armour or weapons to deſtroy them, but were able, like
fierce and cruel beaſts, to ſwallow them up alive, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo weak and
ſo little a flock.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172313:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 4.</hi> Then the Waters had drowned us, and the
ſtream had gone over our ſoul.</head>
               <p>Terrible is the rage of fire, but much more terrible is the
violence and rage of water, for that no power can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. Now, ſaith
<hi>David,</hi> like as huge and mighty floods of water carried with great
power and violence, do ſuddenly overthrow and bear down whatſoever they
meet withall: even ſuch is the rage of the enemies of Gods Church, which no
power of man is able to withſtand. Therefore let us learn to truſt to the
Lords defence and ſuccour. For what elſe is the Church, but as a little
boat tyed by a River fide, and by violence of the water ſoon carried away? Or
as a Reed which by force of the ſtream is eaſily plucked up and carried
away? Such was the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Davids</hi> time, being
compared to the Gentiles round about them. Such is the Church likewiſe at
this day, compared to the adverſaries. Such is every one of us in reſpect
of the force and power of the malignant ſpirit. We are like a Reed which is
eaſily plucked up: and he like a raging flood which with great might and
violence overthroweth and carrieth away all things. We are like a withered
leaf, ſoon blown from the tree; and he like a mighty wind or tempeſt, not
onely blowing down leaves, but plucking up and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing trees and all.
What are we then poor wretches able to do of our own power and ſtrength for
our defence? We muſt learn therefore by faith wholly to reſt upon the word.
For what is our victory but even our faith? Albeit that armour and munitions
have their place, yet can they nothing help at all, unleſs we have a truſt
and affiance in the Lord, who hath promiſed to be our God, our ſtrength,
and our defence: whoſe power is ſuch, whoſe mighty arm alſo is
ſtretched out for the defence of his, that albeit ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great a
tempeſt or violent rage of water ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the pooreſt and
ſimpleſt cottage that can be, it forceth not. Let this be then our
aſſured truſt, let this be the rock of our ſafety, help and ſuccour,
that God will be our defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and keeper, that the great floods and mighty
waters carry us not away. This ſure defence and mighty prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172313:6"/>of our God, the wicked neither know nor believe; for they
attribute all their ſucceſs and welfare to their own ſtrength, wiſdom,
and riches. But <hi>Solomon,</hi> albeit he was a King abundantly endued with
all theſe things, yet ſaith he: <hi>Except the Lord build the houſe, the
builders labour in vain: Except the Lord keep the City, they watch in vain that
keep it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 5.</hi> Then had the ſwelling waters gone over
our ſoul.</head>
               <p>He ſetteth out yet more lively and as it were before their
eyes, the great danger from the which God had delivered them. And this vehement
kind of ſpeech which he uſeth here, had as great force to make the faithful
to feel from what terrible deſtruction they were delivered by the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
hand of God, as if their danger had been preſent before their eyes, and ſo
to become more thankful to God for the ſame.<note place="margin">Note who are
moſt thankfull.</note> For he is thankful to God indeed for his deliverance
and ſafety, which doth acknowledge that before his delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he ſaw
nothing elſe but utter deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>David</hi> ſetteth out the afflictions. and
calamities of the Church and of the godly, whom the world doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hate,
but cruelly Perſecute. Whereby we may ſee that it hath not only a greedy
deſire, but alſo power to hurt, murder and deſtroy. Satan likewiſe
goeth about like a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour. Beſides
theſe, there are great and horrible ſins ſticking in our fleſh. That we
fall not therefore every moment into deſperation, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe periſh,
it is becauſe he is greater which is in us, then he which is in the world, or
the whole world beſides, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith: <hi>If God had not been
with us, our enemies had ſwallowed us up alive.</hi> Now he addeth a notable
ſimilitude, wherewith he amplifieth the danger of the godly, and power of the
wicked.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 6.</hi> Praiſed be the Lord, which hath not
given us as a Prey unto their Teeth.</head>
               <p>He exhorteth the faithſul to be thankful for their
delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:172313:7"/>and expreſſeth unto them, how and (as it
were) with what words they ſhould declare this thankfullneſs. Wherein he
ſetteth forth yet further by another ſimilitude, that it could not be but
they muſt utterly have periſhed, if God had not miraculouſly defended
them. For they were, ſaith he, no otherwiſe preſerved, then as if a man
ſhould violently take a Prey out of the jaws of a raging and cruel beaſt.
As if he ſaid, We were indeed like ſilly ſheep, and as a Prey ready to be
devoured of cruel beaſts: but praiſed be the Lord our God, which would not
ſuffer us ſo to periſh. He ſaith not: <hi>which hath delivered us:</hi>
albeit he did indeed mightily deliver them: but, <hi>which hath not given us as
a Prey, &amp;c.</hi> For this is it which ſpecially the Holy Ghoſt here
ſetteth forth, that the wicked cannot hurt the godly, be they never ſo
many, mighty, furious, cruell and terrible, like to raging and violent waters,
like to cruel and outragious beaſts, falling upon them with open mouth,
except the Lord give them into their hands. Let us therefore with
<hi>David</hi> ſing praiſes unto the Lord our God, which keepeth and
defendeth us, that the raging and cruel beaſts which have ſharpened their
teeth to devour us, cannot hurt us. Without this merciful protection of our
God, there is no way to ſtand againſt Satan and his cruell members the
ſpace of one moment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 7.</hi> Our Soul is eſcaped even as a bird out
of the ſnare of the Fouler: The ſnare is broken, and we are
delivered.</head>
               <p>He amplifieth yet further by a third ſimilitude, the great
perills and dangers of the faithful, being in the hands of their enemies, as a
bird that is taken in the ſnare is in the hands of the fouler; and yet
notwithſtanding they eſcaped by the mighty power of God, no otherwiſe
then the bird that is delivered out of the ſnare of the fouler. By the
ſnare is here to be underſtood as well the fraud and ſubtilty of the
enemies, whereby the Iſraelites were brought into thraldom and captivity, as
alſo the ſtrength and power wherewith they were long oppreſſed. So that
they had not onely to do with Bloody and Cruel Enemies, but alſo 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172313:7"/>were entrapped and ſnared by fraud and ſubtilty, and with
might and power miſerably oppreſſed. Thus being unable both in Strength
and Policy to withſtand their Enemies, they were every way in danger of Death
and Deſtruction: whereby it appeareth that they were miraculouſly
delivered.</p>
               <p>And here have we an Image of our ſpiritual Thraldom and
Captivity under Satan, in whoſe ſnares we were once moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably
wrapped. Now therefore that we are delivered by the ineſtimable benefit of
Chriſt, let us acknowlege both our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Calamity, and the Liberty of this
Grace wherein we ſtand, and let us beware that we caſt not our ſelves
into the ſnares of ſervile Bondage any more. For Satan ſleepeth not, but
lyeth continually in wait for us, ready to draw us into thoſe ſnares again,
out of the which by the great mercy of God we were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered: yea and
ſometimes is ſuffered to hurt either our Bodies or Souls, not only to
ſhew us that he is able likewiſe to deſtroy both Body and Soul, if God
did ſo permit: but alſo to ſtir us up to Faith and Prayer, that we
ſhould call upon him for Aid and Succour againſt theſe perillous Snares,
and being delivered, ſhould give him thanks and praiſe for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Moreover, every Tentation is a Snare, whether it be of the
Fleſh or Spirit. Perſecution, Torments, Impriſonment, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
diſeaſes and infirmities of the Body, be ſnares; which as they are
permitted of God to exerciſe and ſtrengthen our Faith: ſo by the malice
of Satan they are wrought to afflict and to vex men, that he may bring them to
infidelity and deſperation, and ſo into the Snares of eternal Death. From
the which Snares, but by the ſpecial Grace of God, there is no way to
eſcape.</p>
               <p>Thus our life lyeth always open to the Snares of Satan,<note place="margin">The Snares of Satan.</note> and we as ſilly Birds are like at
every moment to be carried away. Notwithſtanding the Lord maketh a way for us
to eſcape. Yea when Satan ſeemeth to be moſt ſure of us, by the mighty
Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God the Snares are broken, and we are delivered. Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hereof
we have in thoſe which are inwardly afflicted, and with heavineſs of Spirit
grievouſly oppreſſed; that when they ſeem to be in utter Deſpair, and
ready (as you would ſay) now to periſh, yet even at the laſt pinch, and
in the uttermoſt Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, cometh the ſweet Comfort of Gods holy Spirit,
and raiſeth them up again. When we are moſt ready to periſh, then is 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172313:8"/>God moſt ready to help.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi>
94.</note> 
                  <hi>Except the Lord had holpen me</hi> (ſaith David) <hi>my Soul
had almoſt dwelt in ſilence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 8.</hi> Our help is in the Name of the Lord who
hath made both Heaven and Earth.</head>
               <p>This is the Concluſion of Thankſgiving, containing a worthy
ſentence of great Comfort, that againſt Sin, the horrour of Death,<note place="margin">The Name of the Lord is our only Sanctuary and ſuccour in all
afflictions.</note> and other Dangers, there is no other help or ſafety but
only <hi>the Name of the Lord.</hi> If that were not <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> we
ſhould fall into all manner of Sin, Blaſphemy, Errors, and into all kind of
Calamities. But our help is in the Name of the Lord, which preſerveth our
Faith and our Life againſt the Devil and the World. And as ye heard in the
other Verſes before, ſo he ſheweth in this verſe alſo, that God
ſuffereth his Saints to be tempted, and in their Tentation to fall into great
Diſtreſs, as even now ready to be drowned and ſwallowed up preſently
with great floods of Water: yet notwithſtanding this Comfort he ſheweth
them, that he will not utterly forſake them. By the which Examples we may
learn to know the Will of the Lord, and to ſeek our help and ſafety at his
hands, which ſuffereth his People to be exerciſed in the Furnace of
<hi>Egypt,</hi> not to their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Deſtruction, but only to kill the old man
with his vain hope and confidence which he hath in his own ſtrength. This is
the cauſe why God ſuffereth his People to be exerciſed. For it is not
hearing, reading, talking, or teaching, nor Speculation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which maketh a
Chriſtian man, but Practice is that which ſpecially is required in a true
Chriſtian, that is to ſay, the Croſs, to pluck down the fleſh and bring
it to nothing; That man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing of his own ſtrength, and ſeeing no
ſuccour in himſelf, ſhould reſign himſelf wholly unto the Lord,
looking with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Hope for help at his hand: for this is the Will of
God. Neither muſt we imagine to our ſelves any other God then ſuch an one
as will help the afflicted and oppreſſed with Deſperation and other
Calamities. To know this Doctrine is one piece of the victory. For they that
know it not when Tentation aſſaileth them, either do deſpair or ſeek
other helps. Let us learn then out of this Pſalm, that it is the Will of God
to exerciſe his Saints with troubles and afflictions: Who ſuffereth great
floods <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172313:8"/>of Water to run over their heads: who alſo
permitteth them to fall into the Snares of the Wicked, and tryeth every Way,
not to deſtroy them, but to ſhew them what they are of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and
ſo to teach them to truſt in his ſaving health. But the fleſh looketh
to the power and multitude of the Adverſaries, and her own infirmity: but to
look unto God, and to hope for his help and ſuccour, it is not able.</p>
               <p>Wherefore this is a neceſſary Concluſion: <hi>Our help is
in the Name of the Lord.</hi> It is a ſhort-Sentence, but it ſetteth forth
moſt worthy Doctrine and Conſolation: whereof ſpecially in theſe latter
days we have great need, ſeeing the Pope, together with the greateſt part
of the Princes and Rulers of the World, ſo cruelly do perſecure the
Doctrine of the Goſpel. In reſpect of theſe huge Mountains, what are we
ſmall Molehils? Yea tho there were no Force nor Power of man for us to fear,
how are we able to ſtand againſt, not only ſo many Devils, but even the
very gates of Hell alſo? And yet this Experience we have of the great Mercy
and Goodneſs of the Lord our God, that when we are even in their hands, and
never ſo much oppreſſed, yet are we not forſaken, but are ſafe
through our Confidence and truſt in his Help.<note place="margin">The fruit of
afflictions.</note> But to this Wiſdom it is impoſſible for us to attain
without continual afflictions: whereby it is neceſſary that the confidence
of all worldly ſuccours ſhould be beaten down. For vexation and trouble
bringeth Underſtanding (as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith,) whereby we are
compelled to cry; <hi>Help Lord, for elſe we periſh.</hi> So in the laſt
hour when Death approacheth, there is nothing wherein mans Heart can repoſe
it ſelf or find Comfort, but his truſt and confidence in the help of the
Lord; There is reſt and quietneſs, there is perfect Peace. He that can then
ſay, <hi>My Help is in the Name of the Lord,</hi> dyeth hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, and is out
of all danger. Thus we may learn what it is to have and enjoy God, even to
reſt in the ſure truſt of his merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful help and ſuccour in all
dangers. Theſe are the Words there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of a victorious and triumphing Faith:
<hi>Our help is in the name of the Lord which made Heaven and Earth.</hi> As if
he ſaid: The maker of Heaven and Earth is my God and my helper. Shew me a God
(O ye my Adverſaries) like unto him. What are your ſnares and your traines
then, compared unto this God? What are your threatnings, your Power, your
Policies? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:172313:9"/>
               <p>Thus he ſetteth the Eternal God, the maker of Heaven and
Earth, againſt all terrours and dangers, againſt the floods and
overflowings of all tentations, and ſwalloweth up as it were with on breath,
all the raging furies of the whole World, and of Hell it ſelf, even as a
little drop of Water is ſwallowed up of a mighty flaming fire. And what is
the World with all his Force and Power, in reſpect of him which made Heaven
and Earth? Let the World fret then, let it rage, ſo that this ſuccour never
fail us. And if it be the Will of God that we ſhall ſuffer trouble and
affliction, yet in him we ſhall overcome at length.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Psalm 125" type="commentary">
            <head>THE COMMENTARY OF Dr. <hi>MARTIN L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THER,</hi> Upon the CXXV
PSALM.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>They that truſt in the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Pſalm going before,<note place="margin">The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the
Pſalm.</note> is a Thankſgiving or a Sacrifice of Praiſe, becauſe the
Godly ſee, and by experience feel that the Lord is faithful and helpeth them
in the time of need. This Pſalm following containeth alſo, in a manner, the
ſame matter: For it pertaineth to the Doctrine of Faith, and exhorteth the
Faithful likewiſe to a ſure truſt and aſſiance in the help of the 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172313:9"/>Lord in all their neceſſities: Whereunto he ſtirreth
them up with great and excellent promiſes. It may alſo be eaſily
under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by that which we have ſaid before. For herein conſiſteth
all this Heavenly Wiſdom, that we do utterly remove out of our ſight,
whatſoever fleſh can comprehend, and believe that which the Word only
telleth us, even againſt all that which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we know, feel, or ſee: And
therefore this Wiſdom is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all humane Wiſdom and Reaſon. For by
Reaſon, and all that Reaſon can comprehend, we feel, ſee, and conceive
all things contrary to that which Faith leadeth us unto.</p>
            <p>He that lyeth ſick at the point of Death, can by Reaſon
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nothing elſe but the imagination of Death. But a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man
leaving his imagination, knoweth that in Death there is true Life. But thou
wilt ſay: He ſeeth and feeleth Death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but Life he cannot feel. I
Anſwer, that becauſe he reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon the Word, and after it he judgeth,
and not after his own feeling, therefore even in Death he ſeeth nothing but
Life, and in the midſt of Darkneſs moſt clear light. For like as God
maketh all things of nothing, and of darkneſs light: ſo he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by his
Word, that in Death there is nothing but life.<note place="margin">The power of
the Word. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.</note> They then which ſtick to the Word and
Promiſe of God, and follow the ſame, do find it true which <hi>David</hi>
ſaith, <hi>He ſpake the Word and it was done,</hi> &amp;c. But before we
can come to this experience, we muſt abide ſome trouble, and therefore have
need of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation as this Pſalm here ſetteth forth.</p>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 1.</hi> They that truſt in the Lord, ſhall be
as Mount Sion, which cannot be removed, but remaineth for ever.</head>
               <p>The Prophet uſeth here a ſimilitude of Mount <hi>Sion,</hi>
becauſe <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> wherein <hi>Sion</hi> ſtood, when the Temple
was builded had moſt ample and notable promiſes of God (as appeareth in
very many places of the Prophets) that it ſhould ſtand ſure and
invincible for ever againſt all troubles and Calamities, for that the Lord
had his abiding and dwelling there; according to that promiſe where he
ſaith, <hi>Here is my reſt, here will I dwell,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore
<hi>David</hi> in another Pſalm glorieth on this wiſe: <hi>Lo, the Kings
were gathered and went together, when they ſaw it, they marvelled; They were
aſtonied and ſuddenly driven back.</hi> As we <pb n="14" facs="tcp:172313:10"/>may ſee
it came to paſs under <hi>Ezechias</hi> in the great Deſtruction of the
<hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and other Kings, as the ſtories witneſs; which
ſhew that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> remained ſafe in all dangers, not by
ſtrength and Policy of the inhabitants, but by the miraculous Work of God
dwelling in it, and thus mightily preſerving and beautifying his own
Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>Now therefore, ſaith he, like as Mount <hi>Sion</hi> and our
Holy City <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is never moved, but remaineth ſure and ſafe
by the mighty protection of the Lord in all Extremities: ſo he that
truſteth in the Lord ſhall be defended againſt the furious Rage of the
World and the Gates of Hell for ever Note how he commandeth no Work here to be
done, as in Popery, in the time of trouble men were taught to enter into ſome
kind of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to faſt, to go on Pilgrimage, and to do ſuch other
fooliſh Works of Devotion, which they deviſed, as an high Service unto God,
and thereby thought to make Condigne Satisfaction for Sin,<note place="margin">To
hope and truſt in the Lord, is tke greateſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that we can do to
him.</note> and merit Eternal Life; but ſimply he leadeth us the plain Way
unto God, pronouncing this to be the chiefeſt Anchor of our Salvation, only
to hope and truſt in the Lord, and that this is the greateſt Service that
we can do unto God. For this is the Nature of God (as I have ſaid) to create
all things of nothing. Therefore he createth and bringeth forth in Death Life;
in Darkneſs,<note place="margin">The Nature of Faith.</note> Light: And this to
believe, is the very Nature and moſt ſpecial Property of Faith. When God
then ſeeth ſuch a one as agreeth with his own Nature, that is, which
believeth to find in Danger, Help; in Poverty, Riches; in Sin,
Righteouſneſs; and that for Gods own Mercies ſake in Chriſt alone; him
can God neither hate nor forſake. For he ſerveth and worſhipeth God truly
which putteth his whole truſt in the Mercy of God. With this Service God is
highly pleaſed, becauſe he delighteth of nothing to make ſomething. So he
made the World of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: ſo he raiſeth up the Poor and Oppreſſed;
ſo he juſtifieth the Sinner; ſo he raiſeth the Dead; and ſo he
ſaveth the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Who ſo then conſenteth to Gods Nature, and obeyeth
his Will, there hoping ſor ſomething where nothing is, he it is that
pleaſeth God, and ſhall never be moved.</p>
               <p>But thou muſt beware that thou imagine not to thy ſelf a
falſe Hope, contrary to the Word of God and thy Vocation. Whereof if thou be
certain, and abide in the ſame, if troubles <pb n="15" facs="tcp:172313:10"/>riſe,
truſt in the Lord; and if he help not in his good time, take me and
<hi>David</hi> alſo for Lyars. Satan will trouble, vex and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort
thee, yea and peradventure make thee to believe that thou art utterly
forſaken; but if thou truſt in the Lord, thou ſhalt feel his help with
joyful Victory. So in the Council of <hi>Auſpurge</hi> when the Princes were
bent againſt us with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, our cauſe ſeemed to be utterly
overthrown. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding yet we live and enjoy ſuch Peace and Liberty
as we would wiſh, maugre the Rage and Malice of the Pope and all the
Adverſaries of the World. With ſuch Conflicts we muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed
leaſt we be diſcouraged when we ſee our cauſe begin to quaile. But the
greater the danger is, the more ſtedfaſtly we muſt truſt. So ſhall it
come to paſs that when we are overcome, yet we ſhall overcome, and the
Conqueror ſhall yield unto us Triumph and Victory.</p>
               <p>This is it that the Pſalm here ſetteth forth: <hi>They that
truſt in the Lord ſhall be as Mount Sion, which cannot be removed, but
remaineth for ever.</hi> And here we have a ſingular promiſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we
are aſſured that we ſhall ſtand and abide for ever If then we do not
continue, it is our own fault, becauſe we abide not firm and ſtable in our
Faith: For this promiſe muſt needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſure and infallible. Yea as it
is impoſſible that God ſhould deny himſelf, and not be God: ſo is it
impoſſible that he ſhould forſake thoſe that put their truſt in
him. But we may not think the time long, but patiently abide the Lords
Leiſure. For Gods power taketh no place in us until we be utterly (to ſpeak
after the manner of the Scripture) exininated, that is, ſtript naked of all
Worldly Hope and Helps that man hath in himſelf, and brought to nothing: like
as when he ſaveth a ſhip from drowning, now ready to periſh, and paſt
all Remedy; As the two Stories of the Goſpel, one of the Ship, the other of
the danger of <hi>Peter,</hi> do teſtifie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 2.</hi> As the Mountains are about
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo is the Lord about his People, from henceforth and
for ever.</head>
               <p>Where many hundred thouſands of men are, there are ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſeven thouſand which know God, or believe in God, and yet for their ſakes
the whole Multitude is called God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s people, <pb n="16" facs="tcp:172313:11"/>Even ſo
was it in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> called
holy by the figure Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necdoche where a part is taken for the whole.</note>
Albeit the greater part was Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Godleſs, yet was <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
called Holy, not only in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a ſmall Nnmber of the Godly; but
alſo becauſe God had his abiding there. So when there was not one juſt
perſon in <hi>Sodom</hi> but <hi>Lot</hi> with his two Daughters, yet could
not the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel deſtroy <hi>Sodom</hi> with fire ſo long as <hi>Lot</hi> was
in it. Likewiſe where four or five or ten godly Perſons are to be found,
for their ſakes the whole City is called Holy. For theſe are the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
corner ſtones, theſe are the precious Pearls which God ſo highly
eſteemeth, and for whoſe ſakes he ſpareth the Wicked. Therefore ſaith
<hi>David,</hi> As <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is compaſſed about with Mountains,
ſo doth the Lord compaſs his People and mightily defend them on every
ſide. In like manner <hi>Zachary</hi> Prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of a City whoſe Wall is
of fire. Theſe Similitudes do ſet forth unto us the Safety of Gods People,
that weak and little poor Flock, againſt all Dangers. Upon this promiſe if
we alſo do reſt, which at this day enjoy the ineſtimable Benfit of Gods
Holy Word, we ſhall be defended againſt the Rage of Satan and the whole
World, not by fiery and brazen Walls, but by the Lord himſelf. Theſe things
albeit we cannot comprehend, yet ſhould we believe them ſo certainly as if
we did ſee them with our bodily Eyes. If we ſhould ſee our ſelves
compaſſed about with brazen and fiery Walls, we would be without all fear,
and Triumph againſt Satan. But it is a matter of Faith, not to truſt unto
that which the Eyes ſee, but which the Word offereth and promiſeth. This
one thing therefore is lacking in us, that we have not eyes of the Spirit, but
we judge according to the eyes and ſenſe of the Fleſh. For elſe we
ſhould be no more afraid then they which being cloſed within the Walls of
an invincible Caſtle, fear not the force and power of their Enemies, be they
never ſo terrible. We muſt not doubt therefore, but if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, we are
compaſſed about with fiery and brazen Mountains, that is to ſay, we abide
for ever invincible againſt the Rage of Satan and all the Powers of
Darkneſs. Bleſſed therefore is he that believeth.</p>
               <p>Theſe Mountains are the Angels, which compaſs us on every
ſide, that Satan with his Angels and Miniſters cannot hurt us as he would;
Whoſe Malice and Power is ſuch, that if they did not continually behold us,
continually defend us and watch <pb n="17" facs="tcp:172313:11"/>over us, he would deſtroy
us every moment. This can all they teſtifie which know that Satan is a
Murtherer and a Lyar, which cannot abide to ſee the godly proſper, and
therefore he ſeeketh by all means to root them out from the face of the
Earth. That we are not then utterly conſumed, it is the benefit of theſe
Mountains, by whom we are ſo compaſſed and defended. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Satan
hurleth his Darts at us as it were through the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, to deſtroy us, and
worketh us indeed ſome ſorrow, but he cannot move us.</p>
               <p>This ſimilitude ſeemeth to be taken out of the Story of
<hi>Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus</hi> in the ſecond book of the <hi>Kings,</hi> where the
ſervant of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizeus</hi> ſaw the Hills about him full of fiery
Chariots, and Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men compaſſing <hi>Helizeus</hi> round about, and
mightily defending him. This ſuccour which the Servant of <hi>Helizeus</hi>
ſaw, and the Prophet believed, when he ſaw nothing, is ſaith the Prophet,
round about all them which truſt in the Lord: as alſo the 34. Pſalm
witneſſeth; <hi>The Angel of the Lord pitcheth round about them that fear
him.</hi> But our eyes are ſhut up and ſee not theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, whereof
not with ſtanding we have daily experience.</p>
               <p>This promiſe then will never deceive us; only let us not
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves. If therefore we did believe, no doubt, we ſhould
ſleep, we ſhould live, we ſhould die, yea (that more is) we ſhould
ſuffer what ſoever Satan and the world can do againſt us, without all
fear. For thus ſhould we think, if I ſuffer any thing, it is not without
the Will of God, nor without good cauſe, well known, tho' not unto me, yet
unto God. Therefore although Satan break through the wall in one place, yet
ſhall he never be able utterly to overthrow it altogether. Thus ſhould we
think in our troubles and afflictions, and comfort our ſelves with the good
Will of God. But we are afraid when any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cometh, and never feel that
ſecurity which Faith bringeth. Thus do we worthily ſuffer the puniſhment
of our infidelity which we nouriſh within us, although we be called away from
it by ſo many notable places of Scripture.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this, it is not enough that we are compaſſed
about with fiery Walls, that is, with the ſure Cuſtody, the continual Watch
and Ward of the Angels, but the Lord himſelf is our Wall: ſo that every way
we are defended by the Lord againſt all Dangers. Above us he is a Heaven, on
both ſides he is as a <pb n="18" facs="tcp:172313:12"/>Wall, under us he is as a ſtrong
Rock whereupon we ſtand: ſo are we every way ſure and ſafe. Now, if
Satan through theſe munitions caſt his darts at us, it muſt needs be that
the Lord himſelf ſhall be hurt before we take harm. But great is our
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity, which hear all theſe things in vain. Yet muſt they be taught
and learned, leaſt the time come that we be deſtitute of all Counſel and
Comfort in theſe matters. For certain it is that the hour ſhall come when
we muſt have experience of theſe things, or elſe utterly periſh.</p>
               <p>Where he addeth, <hi>From henceforth and for ever.</hi> By
theſe words he ſheweth that this vigilancy of the Lord our God over us, is
not temporal, but eternal, according to that which he ſaid before in the
firſt verſe of this Pſalm. <hi>They ſhall remain for ever.</hi> Let us
learn therefore out of this Pſalm, that our Conſtancy and perſeverance
conſiſteth in this, that we are defended by the Power and Providence of the
Lord on every ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 3.</hi> For the rod of the Wicked ſhall not
reſt on the lot of the Righteous, leaſt the Righteous put forth their hand
unto Wickedneſs.</head>
               <p>Here the Prophet plainly declareth, that the People which reſt
under this Defence and Protection, are afflicted and ſubject to all
Miſeries and Calamities as touching the fleſh; altho' they be compaſſed
about with ſuch high and mighty Mountains as touching the Spirit, as Satan
can never ſurmount, yet touching the Fleſh and the Old man, they lye open
on every ſide to the Darts of Satan and the World; For God by theſe means
will afflict and exerciſe the Fleſh, that Sin and the fooliſhneſs of
the Fleſh may be mortified in them, and that ſpiritual Wiſdom and the
inward man may increaſe. This is the cauſe why we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the
Fleſh, as a broken Hedge, and as a City whoſe Walls are caſt down, and
ſo lyeth open to the Enemies on every ſide. Wherefore there is no ſort of
men ſo vile and abject which do not think that they may do what they liſt
againſt the true Profeſſors of the Goſpel. Hereof come ſuch
intollerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, horrible blaſphemies, cruel torments and bloody
ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Saints of God. For the Fleſh hath no Walls, no
Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions to defend it, but the Spirit. Therefore the fleſh is in 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172313:12"/>danger to all Storms and Tempeſts, broken and troden down
of the wicked, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, Chap. 51. <hi>Which have ſaid
unto thy Soul, Bow down that we may go over. Thou haſt layed thy Body as the
ground, and as the ſtreet to them that went over.</hi> Theſe afflictions we
muſt needs ſuffer and by patience overcome them, and withal we muſt
beware that by theſe outward afflictions the inward man be not weakened or
overcome; reſting in this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hope and truſt, that the Lord will
never forſake us, but that we are in the boſom of the Father, and are
cloſed within moſt ſure and ſtrong holds. So that now, altho' our
Goods, our Wives, our Children, yea and our Lives alſo be taken from us, yet
we ſhall never be ſpoiled of our Chriſt, by whom we are ſo ſurely
defended, that in the midſt of all our Tentations he will make a way for us
to eſcape, or elſe give us ſtrength to bear them.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee what Conſolations the Holy Ghoſt ſetteth
forth unto them which believe the Word. For unto ſuch as look for a better
Life then this, all things are here full of Calamities and Miſeries. Death
followeth Death, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, and we conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually die. One
Tentation followeth another, until at the length by the Death of the Fleſh
all miſeries ſhall ceaſe and have an end. This verſe therefore maketh
much for our Comfort, admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us that we muſt ſuffer many troubles;
yet ſo, that at the length we ſhall be ſafe and ſet at Liberty from
them all, though not in this Life, yet in the Life to come, and in Eternal
Life. And why ſhould we not thus boldly promiſe unto our ſelves,
remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under this diligent Cuſtody of the Angels, yea of the Lord
himſelf, which is always round about his People? But here (as before I
ſaid) we have need of Faith, that we may judge herein, not according to our
preſent troubles and tentations, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of Promiſe. And
what ſhould we need any promiſes if there were no tentations? which
tentations whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be within in the Spirit, or without in the fleſh,
the time ſhall come when we through Chriſt ſhall have full victory
hereof, as this verſe full of ſweet Conſolation doth promiſe unto
us.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding this promiſe ſeemeth incredible both to us
which ſuffer, and alſo to them which perſecute and afflict us. For if we
behold the ſame with our outward eyes, what can be <pb n="20" facs="tcp:172313:13"/>more
falſe? yea the contrary ſeemeth to be moſt true. Behold our Saviour
Chriſt, was he not ſo forſaken, hanging upon the Croſs, that the Rod or
Scepter of the wicked reſted upon him? Did it not reſt likewiſe upon the
Prophets, the Apoſtles, and other holy Martyrs? This matter then, if we
conſider it with our outward eyes, hath another meaning then the Words do
import. For they promiſe that the Scepter of the wicked ſhall have no power
over the godly, and yet all ſtories and examples do teftify the contrary.
Therefore the Holy Ghoſt calleth us back to the purpoſe and Couſel of God
revealed in his Word, and commandeth us to weigh and conſider, not what we
ſuffer and with our outward eyes behold, but what is decreed with the Lord in
Heaven. And he that can ſo ſequeſter himſelf from the beholding of his
afflictions and tentations, and yield himſelf wholly over to the Will of God,
and there reſt, is a right Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; yea he that is ignorant hereof, in true
Divinity know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing at all. For what knoweth he which is ignorant that
God is ſuch a God as will not ſuffer the godly to be oppreſſed of the
wicked? For ſeeing he hath ſaid, <hi>I am the Lord thy God,</hi> he will
never ſuffer that which is his own, to be wreſted either by the World or by
the gates of Hell out of his hands. If he then abide and continue, they ſhall
alſo continue for ever which are his. Thus to believe, and thus to lay hold
on things invifible, is true Divinity and true ſpiritual Wiſdom indeed,
whereupon we may ground this Propoſition out of the inviſible Counſel of
God; God hateth the wicked, and loveth the juſt, <hi>ergo</hi> he will damn
and deſtroy the wicked, and will deliver and ſave the juſt. And here we
ſee that which is the chiefeſt thing in all the Pſalms and Prophets, to
ſpring of the firſt Precept: <hi>I am the Lord thy God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now have we to learn how we may apply this verſe rightly and
to our Comfort. For true Divinity conſiſteth in uſe and practice. We are
vexed on every ſide with cruel Biſhops, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Princes, and others which
hate the Word of God and the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which we profeſs. But theſe are very
trifles, if ye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with thoſe vexations which Satan, Sin, and our
own infirmity raiſe up in our Conſciences. We muſt learn therefore thus
to judge of all theſe things, that they are the Rod and Scepter of the
wicked, and to ſet the Lord againſt them, reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="21" facs="tcp:172313:13"/>his Will here in his Word, and pronouncing that he will not ſuffer
the Scepter of the wicked to reſt upon the godly. Seeing then the ſame
Prince promiſeth thus much unto us which hath all things in his hand, what
can we require more? For the will of God is certain, that though he ſuffer us
to be afflicted, yet will he not ſee us troden under foot or periſh. Thus
muſt we apply theſe ſweet Conſolations.</p>
               <p>What the rod ſigniſieth in the Scripture it is well known.
Children when they are young, are corrected with a rod; and when they wax
bigger, with a Wand or Cudgel; and if they will not ſo amend, then followeth
the Iron rod. Hereof it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the rod ſignifieth all Power and Rule,
which is for the Amendment and Correction of ſuch as do offend. So it is
taken in the 110 Pſalm. <hi>The Lord ſhall ſend forth the rod of thy
Power out of Sion:</hi> That is to ſay, thy Kingdom; For there he
ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth ſuch a rod whereby Kingdoms and People are governed. On this
wiſe the holy Ghoſt permitteth here to the wicked, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and Tyranny
over the godly, which they are compelled to ſuffer. Like as we are compelled
not only to ſee but alſo to ſuffer the Tyranny of Antichriſt and the
Power of his Kingdom, perſecuting, deſtroying and murthering the
Chriſtians, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging againſt them with all kind of Tyranny. Yea we are
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled moreover to ſuffer the Tyranny of Satan vexing and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying my
Heart and the Hearts of the Brethren which believe in Chriſt. This Dominion
or Tyranny the Holy Ghoſt calleth the rod of the wicked; and comforteth us,
that as the Lord liveth, their Tyranny ſhall fall, and ſhall not reſt
upon the Lot of the godly.</p>
               <p>The lot of the juſt is as much to ſay as the Portion, that
is, the Number or Congregation of the juſt. Like as Chriſt calleth them the
<hi>Little Flock,</hi> and <hi>Paul, The poor Saints.</hi> Over theſe,
ſaith he, although the Tyrants do rule, yet ſhall not their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er endure.
Although the Perſecutors of the Church do oppreſs the faithful, yet ſhall
they not do ſo always, neither ſhall their Counſels have the ſucceſs
which they deſire. For they think to root out this Doctrine for ever; but
that ſhall they never be able to do: Therefore albeit ye ſuffer in the mean
time, ſaith the Holy Ghoſt, yet know ye, that my will is, <hi>That they
which believe in me ſhall never periſh, but ſhall be preſerved to Life
Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting.</hi> 
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:172313:14"/>Here then have ye whereunto ye may
truſt in all your Tentations.</p>
               <p>But behold the reaſon which the Holy Ghoſt here uſeth to
prove that the Scepter of the wicked ſhall not reſt upon the juſt. God is
moved ſaith he, to help and defend the juſt. For elſe it might ſo come
to paſs that God ſhould have no Church at all, and the juſt ſhould put
forth their hands to Wickedneſs. So we find in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> that before
the People were delivered into the hands of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> they had
promiſe that after ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years they ſhould return again to
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe they ſhould not be brought into doubt of Gods
Mercy, and ſo utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſpair, and falling away from God ſhould turn to
Gentiliſm; as it is in the Pſalm, leaſt the godly ſhould turn to
fooliſhneſs, that is to ſay, ſhould blaſpheme and become impatient,
This is the cauſe why God joyneth the promiſe of the Word with the
Execution and Performance of the Deed; or elſe the godly ſhould be driven
to Deſperation. We ſee how many are caſt down with Adverſity by the
loſs of Goods, Wife, Children, and other things which are dear unto them.
Except therefore their minds were raiſed up again and comforted, firſt,
with the Word and Promiſe, and then, with the Performance and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of
the ſame, many would ſay there were no God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God muſt needs
ſhew himſelf to be a God, not only in Word but alſo in Deed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> had great promiſes of God, and yet by his own
Son he was driven out of his Kingdom, and ſo perſecuted that he was
compelled to fly away barehead and barefoot. This was a ſore Tentation.
Wherefore the great and ample Promiſes made unto him could never have
raiſed him up and comforted him again, except God had indeed delivered him
out of this great miſery and affliction. Even ſo if we had no more but the
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God to ſupport us againſt the Papiſts and Adverſaries of
the Word, yea if God did not indeed fight for us and defend us againſt their
Tyranny, we ſhould be ſwallowed up with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and brought even to
Deſperation. God therefore worketh both ways; he raiſeth up with the Word
and Promiſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livereth out of troubles and afflictions by Execution of
the deed, that according to the ſaying of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the tentation
ſhould not be above our ſtrength, but ſhould have an end, and we learn 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172313:14"/>by our own Experience that the firſt Commandment, <hi>I
am the Lord thy God,</hi> is moſt certain and infallible Therefore when he
ſaith, <hi>Leaſt the juſt ſhould put forth their hand to
Wickedneſs,</hi> it is as much as if he ſhould ſay, Leaſt the juſt
ſhould turn away from God and fall to Gentiliſm. For God hath a double care
over the Faithful; firſt, that they be not overcome, but may overcome the
tentation; and this he doth by the Word and Promiſe. The ſecond is that the
tentation be not perpetual. Even ſo muſt we be undoubtedly perſwaded,
that beſides the infallible promiſes which we have of the good Will of God
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, and in the end of Everlaſting Life, we ſhall be alſo
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and our Adverſaries deſtroyed, albeit we can ſee no manner of
way or poſſible means how it may be done. This is it then that this verſe
here ſetteth forth, that God is ſo careful for the ſafety of his People,
that he ſeemeth to fear leaſt they ſhould put forth their hand to
Wickedneſs, and fall away from him, whereby it might come to paſs that he
ſhould have no People, and ſo there ſhould be no God. For God is the God
of the living, and therefore he muſt needs have a People. Wherefore there
muſt ever be ſome remaining which may praiſe and worſhip Him. If there
muſt needs be ſuch a Number remaining, God muſt of neceſſity make an
end alſo of tentations.</p>
               <p>But here we muſt beware that we do not appoint the time of
this deliverance. For before that come, God will have us tryed to the
uttermoſt, and brought to that Extremity, that all our hope and truſt
ſhall be utterly ſpent, and we at the point of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. Now, when we
are brought into this caſe that we can ſee nothing but Deſperation, then,
even then God ſendeth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, in Death, he ſheweth Life; and even in
Damnation, he bringeth Salvation: briefly, of nothing he maketh all things, and
when all hope of Remedy is paſt, then beginneth he to work, and frameth all
new again in moſt perfect wiſe. Thus cannot the God of this World do. This
is the fingular work of God therefore, that when thou thinkeſt thy ſelf
clean caſt away and utterly forlorn, even then thou ſhouldſt be moſt
ſure and ſafe, and moſt gloriouſly ſhine as the day Star in the
Firmament. Theſe things are eaſily taught, but by Experience we find and
feel how far they paſs all Reaſon and Power of man, and how hardly we can
believe that God maketh all things of nothing, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:172313:15"/>that he is
careful tor us, whether we be afflicted in the Fleſh or in the Spirit, and
that he is more mindful of our deliverance then we our ſelves can be. Theſe
things therefore muſt be often and diligently taught, that we may learn that
Heavenly Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which the firſt Commandment ſetteth forth unto us,<note place="margin">Old things are paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; behold all things are become
new.</note> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our God is ſuch an one as of old things is wont to
make new; of poor, to make rich; of deſpiſed, glorious. And this laſt we
would all gladly have, but that will not be, except Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Poverty go
before.</p>
               <p>Here have we then a ſiugular Promiſe and Conſolation. As
if he ſhould ſay, The Rod of the wicked grieveth you, but be of good
Comfort my People, and patiently endure it, for I will not ſuffer the
tentation ſo far to prevail over you that your Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and truſt in me
ſhall utterly fail you. Storms and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts ſhall ariſe, and your
Dangers ſhall ſeem ſo great as tho the Waves ſhould preſently
ſwallow you up: but I will not ſuffer you to periſh. I will bridle their
Rage and make an end of the rod of the Wicked and Unrighteous, yet will I not
leave you deſtitute of my Righteouſneſs. Thus do Tentations teach us the
true uſe and meaning of the firſt Commandment, the which none without
afflictions and tentations ſhall rightly know or underſtand.</p>
               <p>Moreover we are here admoniſhed of the great danger that
followeth theſe afflictions and tentations, which they that through
impatiency forſake the Word and Faith, do fall into. Therefore the Lord here
ſheweth himſelf ſo careful for his People, leaſt they ſhould fall
into this danger. For their ſtate which have once forſaken the Word, is
much more perillous then it was before; and into ſuch (as our Saviour
Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth in the Goſpel) do enter ſeven Spirits much more
wicked then the firſt. We muſt therefore patiently ſuffer and perſevere
in all tentations, and rather abide all Extremities then once ſhrink from the
Word of Life, leaſt we be poſſeſſed with ſeven Spirits more wicked
then the firſt. And moreover we muſt aſſuredly truſt (as we are
taught it this verſe) that ſo long as we have a deſire and purpoſe ſo
to do, the Lord will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for ſake us or ſuffer us to fall into this
impiety. For here have we a manifeſt promiſe and a lively deſcription of
the Lords ſingular care and providence over us, namely that he is mindful 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172313:15"/>of the end of our tentations and afflictions, ſo that we
only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue conſtant and patient unto the end. And if the Heathen Poet
ſaid, Endure and reſerve your ſelves for more happy things, how much more
ſhould Chriſtians diligently ſtir up themſelves with mutual
Exhortations to Patience and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, whether they outwardly ſuffer
in things pertaining to the Body and to this preſent life, or inwardly in
Conſcience. For we have a God which even in Death, in Hell, and in the
midſt of all our Sins, can ſave and deliver us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 4.</hi> Do well O Lord unto them that be good and
true of heart.</head>
               <p>The Prophet ſaith not here: Do well Lord to the perfect, and
ſuch as offend in nothing: but, <hi>to the good and true of Heart.</hi> The
good and true of Heart, are they which are of a ſingle, ſincere and upright
Heart. For theſe are they which are moſt accepted of God, altho they alſo
through infirmity do ſometimes offend. Now where he prayeth that God will do
well to the good and godly, he meaneth alſo and ſecretly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth that
the godly are in miſery and affliction, and that the ungodly do abound with
all worldly felicity: As we ſee at this day the Enemies of the Goſpel to
enjoy great Riches and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, whereby they vex and oppreſs the godly.
This is a great offence and ſtumbling-block to the godly, and therefore the
Church hath need of this Prayer, That God would do well unto the godly, which
truſt in him, and ſeek his Glory with their whole Heart, that they by
ſtumbling at this offence do not fall away to impiety. This Prayer containeth
in it a Prophecy with a promiſe, that like as he prayeth for the
Bleſſing, Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and Proſperity of the juſt, ſo at the length it
ſhall alſo come to paſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 5.</hi> But thoſe that turn aſide by their
crooked ways, the Lord ſhall lead with the workers of Iniquity: but peace
ſhall be upon <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>He ſaith not ſimply, ſuch as turn aſide, but ſuch as
turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide by their own Wickedneſs. For to give place to tentations by
infirmity of the Fleſh, or weakneſs of Mind, or elſe of Faith, 
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172313:16"/>and ſo to decline from the right way, (which cometh to
paſs ſometimes even in the Saints, as the Example of <hi>Peter</hi>
teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) is one thing, and to fall away through wickedneſs and
perverſneſs of Heart, is another: which cannot be in the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God,
but properly belongeth to the wicked and godleſs. This ſort of men hath
ever corrupted the Church from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, and with a ſhew of
holineſs hath deceived the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which becauſe God puniſheth them
not, but ſpareth them and ſuffereth them to proſper in this World, become
ſo proud that they will be counted amongſt the holieſt, and of the World
are ſo commonly taken. We ſee that not only the godly are mixed with the
wicked in this World, but in the Lords floore alſo the Wheat lyeth hidden
under the Chaſſe. We muſt pray therefore that God would bring theſe
Hypocrites to light, and give unto them their juſt Puniſhment with the
workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Then ſhall peace enſue to the Church of God. For
whilſt the Lord poureth forth his vengeance upon the wicked which vex and
perſecute his true members, he gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the good and upright of
Heart, and openly declareth his fatherly good will and tender love towards
them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Psalm 129" type="commentary">
            <head>The Commentary of Dr. <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> upon the
<hi>CXXIX Pſalm.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>They have oftentimes afflicted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis Pſalm conſiſteth of two parts.<note place="margin">The
Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Pſalm.</note> In the former he giveth thanks to God for the
defence and continual deliverance of the People of God. In the latter part he
maketh his Prayer againſt the Adverſaries, and in praying he propheſieth
withal. Both theſe ſerve for our inſtruction, and alſo contain an
Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation <pb n="27" facs="tcp:172313:16"/>to patience under the Croſs, which
pertaineth not to one age or time, but as the continual Hiſtory of the Church
doth ſhew, to all times, and to the whole life of man. Moreover we do here
comprehend both Churches, of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo in a manner joyneth them both together, when he
ſaith, <hi>Firſt to the Jew, and then to the Grecian.</hi> For as touching
the Church or People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> it appeareth by the Hiſtories,
that they were placed in the midſt of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as a goodly Roſe in
the midſt of Thornes. On the Eaſt ſide, the <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> the
<hi>Arabians,</hi> and other cruel People vexed them. On the South part, the
<hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> the <hi>Troglodites,</hi> the
<hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and other like. On the North ſide, the
<hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> &amp;c. So the Church after the deſtruction of the
Synagogue, is compaſſed every way with Enemies, and Chriſt, according to
the Pſalm, reigneth in the midſt of his Enemies. Thus were they oftentimes
and many ways afflicted. But herewithal God ſhewed this miracle, that when
they were ſo afflicted, he always delivered them. And thus was the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
of <hi>Iſrael</hi> a miraculous Kingdom, in that the Lord when he would
correct and chaſtiſe them, ſuffered the <hi>Philiſtines, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites,
Moabites, Aſſyrians</hi> and <hi>Babylonians</hi> to have victory over
them. Again, when they ſeemed to be utterly oppreſſed, they
victoriouſly prevailed againſt their Enemies. So continued this Kingdom in
deſpite of the cruel Nations round about it, and of Satan himſelf: as is to
be ſeen in the Books of the <hi>Kings</hi> and alſo of the
<hi>Chronicles.</hi> Now, becauſe this People had both threatnings and
promiſes ſet before them, as touching their afflictions and deliverance,
this was unto them a great Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, even when they were afflicted and
ſpoiled, that they knew that all theſe things came to paſs not by the
Will or Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their Enemies, and much-leſs by their Righteouſneſs or
Deſerts, but only by the Will of God thus puniſhing and chaſtiſing his
People, yea threatning and forewarning them by the Prophets, that he would ſo
puniſh the diſobedient. This is no ſmall Conſolation, that in thy
Affliction and Calamity thou mayeſt be able to ſay; This is the ſcourge
of God, thus correcting me, and viſiting my Sins; It is not the Wrath of God,
or the merit and deſerving of my Adverſary.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:172313:17"/>
            <p>Theſe things muſt we apply unto our ſelves alſo, to the
end that when we be oppreſſed, we may comfort our ſelves that we are not
oppreſſed by the power of Death, Sin, Hell, or any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the
will of God our Creator, afflicting us and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing our Sins and
ingratitude; and yet ſo, that he leaveth unto us this fatherly promiſe,
that he will not forſake us. And ſuch a figure of the whole Kingdom of
Chriſt is ſet forth in the <hi>Apocalyps.</hi> For how much doth it ſpeak
of evil Angels, of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el beaſts, and ſuch other Plagues of the Church,
which ſhould enter into the Church and the Kingdom of Chriſt, God ſo
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting? Notwithſtanding Conſolation followeth afflictions and
calamities, and though the Church be never ſo ſore afflicted, yet ſhall
it continue and endure, and at the length ſhall overcome and victoriouſly
triumph.</p>
            <p>But this Pſalm agreeth eſpecially unto our time, wherein the
Church hath been moſt grievouſly afflicted both under the <hi>Turks</hi>
and alſo under the <hi>Romiſh</hi> biſhops, yea and as it were utterly
aboliſhed: So that if ye weigh the matter well, it may appear that the
Condition of the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Babylon</hi> was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the ſtate
of the Church under Antichriſt; where the true uſe of the Sacraments was
taken away, the benefit of Chriſt darkned, faith extinguiſhed, no true
ſervice of God uſed, no true good works exerciſed; gnerally, all things
which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to true Religion were clean aboliſhed, or moſt miſerably
deformed and defaced. Wherefore, like as the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>
were put from the ſight and uſe of the Temple, the Sacrifices, the
Ceremonies, and all politick Government: ſo the Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Antichriſt
had no true miniſtry, no true ſervice of God, not her own Kingdom and
Government, but was conſtrained to obſerve and keep the Heatheniſh Rites
and Ceremonies of the Papiſts. Thus was the Wrath, and thus have been the
Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God in a manner all one, in the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi>
and the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore it is moſt neceſſary that we lay hold upon this
Conſolation, that, as the Pſalm ſaith, We are afflicted, we are caſt
down, we are troden under foot, but we are not overcome. For the Church ſhall
ſtand and remain invincible, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that through great
incredulity and incredible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, the victory thereof is hidden and cannot
be ſeen. As <pb n="29" facs="tcp:172313:17"/>it was under the <hi>Pope,</hi> where all
Schools and all Churches taught nothing elſe but the blaſphemous Doctrine
of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Biſhops, and doting Dreams of the Monks. This was
the very ſame thing that the Pſalm 73. complaineth of, where it ſaith,
<hi>We ſee not our ſignes:</hi> and yet God had even then his Church,
although it was very little, obſcure, and miſerably deformed. Before the
Kingdom of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Antichriſt, what a ſwarw of Hereticks
ſprang up? Of whom alſo the Church was ſore vexed and afflicted, even as
the <hi>Jews</hi> were afflicted of the Nations which dwelled near unto them.
And like as the Captivity followed that affliction of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo
the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Biſhops was that Captivity which
follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the out ragious fury of the Hereticks, and out of the which alſo
have flowed all the evils, and plagues which have been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince in the
Church, as out of a foul ſink, and filthy pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. But now by the great mercy
of God the Captivity begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be turned, the Temple is repaired, and the
true Service of God reſtored.</p>
            <p>This Pſalm after my judgement, ſpeaketh generally of all
ſuch troubles and afflictions of the Church, as have been at all times and in
all ages; As firſt, that the Kingdom of the <hi>Jews</hi> when they were yet
under good Kings, was mightily aſſailed, but yet not utterly overcome; And
that the people afterwards were ſpoyled of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and
<hi>Babylonians,</hi> and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Captive, but not clean forſaken. For
they were again de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out of Captivity, and in their own land enjoyed the
promiſe concerning Chriſt. Thus ſpeaketh the Pſalm firſt of the
<hi>Jewiſh Church.</hi> Afterwards it comprehendeth as a Prophecy, the State
and Condition of the Church of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> to wit, that God would
preſerve and defend it againſt all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, againſt all the rage and
fury of the World, againſt the Kingdom of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Antichriſt,
and moreover againſt all the tentations of Sin, which vex and oppreſs the
Conſcience. Thus muſt we apply this Pſalm to all times and ages of the
Church, to all changes and alterations, all dangers of the World, the Fleſh,
Sin, the Law, Death, and the Gates of Hell. For the World aſſaileth it with
power and wiſdom; the Devil, with deſperation and dubitation; Hereticks
with errors in Faith and Religion, and the Conſcience with Sins. In all
theſe Perils we <pb n="30" facs="tcp:172313:18"/>ſay, Bleſſed be the Lord God, who
ſuffereth us not to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above that we are able to bear. Indeed we
muſt be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and tryed, but in the Tentation he will give an outſcape;
beſides this, that he giveth us ſtrength alſo to bear the Tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
until the time of deliverance come. This benefit <hi>David</hi> here ſetteth
forth, and ſheweth unto us the ſtate of his people, to the end we may
thereby learn this Comfort, that like as he p<hi rend="sup">r</hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that People, even
ſo will he alſo preſerve us. For we have one and the ſame God, the
ſame Spirit, the ſame Word, the ſame Promiſes, and briefly all things
elſe whatſoever. Wherefore we may ſay and ſing with <hi>David;</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1,2" type="verse">
               <head>Verſe 1. <hi>They have oftentimes afflicted me from my
youth, may</hi> Iſrael <hi>now ſay:</hi> Verſe 2. <hi>They have
oftentimes afflicted me from my youth, but they could not prevail againſt
me.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>He nameth no certain Enemy, to the end he may compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all.
Where he ſaith, from my youth, he underſtandeth all the time from their
primitive Church (as we call it) until <hi>Iſrael</hi> began firſt to be
the People of God. For albeit we ever praiſe thoſe things which are moſt
ancient and of greateſt anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity (as the primitive Church is indeed worthy
to be praiſed) yet God regardeth not this difference. For in all times, and
even in the laſt ages of the Church he gave notable Prophets, to the people
of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> as before the Captivity, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> of all other
the moſt excellent; after the Captivity, <hi>Aggaus, Zachary</hi> and others.
In the mean time between <hi>Moyſes</hi> and theſe, were <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,
Helizeus,</hi> &amp;c. So we ſee that the Primitive Church was more pure from
Hereticks and wicked Opinions. But yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there were ſome
notable Prophets and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men even in the latter times. And when
the root of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> ſeemed now to be withered, yet God raiſed up
<hi>Anna, Simeon, Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> For God preſerveth his
Church though it be never ſo much aſſailed and oppreſſed, according
to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Only let us open our eyes that we may ſee from whence this
cometh.</p>
               <p>And here we may not look to thoſe things which the World
eſpecially eſteemeth and magnifieth, but we muſt behold the 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172313:18"/>Church as it is afflicted, oppreſſed, and full of
Calamity. For this is the true face of the Church of God, that it is weak,
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with all deadly Engines, and compaſſed with all the furies of
the Devil, the World, the Fleſh, Sin and Death. Theſe things he that will
not behold, but flyeth and abhorreth them, ſhall never find out the true
Church indeed. For that is not the the true picture and image of the Church
which the Painters ſet forth, which paint her as a goodly Virgin, as a City
well armed, adorned and beautified. Indeed that is a true picture, but not
according to the Eyes of the Fleſh. But ſpiritual Eyes do ſee this great
Beauty, that Chriſt is her Husband, and begot her unto himſelf by the Holy
Ghoſt, beautified her and made her glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with his own blood, with his
merits and with his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. Of all theſe things the fleſh can
ſee nothing, can judge nothing, but ſeeth rather the contrary, how ſhe is
ſubject to moſt bitter hatred, malice, vexations and torments. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
if it would paint her out in ſuch ſort as he ſeeth and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her,
then muſt it paint and ſet her forth as a deformed and poor maiden,
ſitting in a dangerous Wood or Deſac, in the midſt of cruel and hungry
Lyons, Bears, Wolve, Swine, and Venemous Serpents: alſo in the midſt of
outragious and furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, attempting with Sword, Fire and Water to deſtroy
her, and to root her out from the face of the Earth. As there is in the
<hi>Apocalyps</hi> ſet forth a goodly Picture,<note place="margin">Chap.
12.</note> (then the which there is nothing more excellent in that book) that
the Church as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate woman, flyeth from the old Serpent or Dragon
perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her and her Child. Wherefore theſe words which <hi>David</hi>
here uſeth, may very well be applied to her: <hi>Many times have mine Enemies
afflicted me, many times have they vexed me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this affliction ſeemeth rather to be an utter
Deſtruction, if we follow the judgment of the fleſh; As if the Enemies did
ſo prevail and overcome, that the Church were utterly oppreſſed and
vanquiſhed for ever: As we all find by our own Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in our Conflicts
which privately we ſuffer in our Hearts, when Satan terrifieth and
confoundeth our Conſciences. For then are raiſed up ſuch terrors, that no
man can otherwiſe judge but that the victory is Satans, oppreſſing us
with heavy and bitter Cogitations, with Tentations, Vexation, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of
Spirit, and ſpoyling us (as to the fleſh it ſeemeth) of all 
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172313:19"/>the ſweet Conſolations which by the merit of Chriſt
and the Word are offered unto us. According to this ſence we may well ſay,
<hi>Oftentimes have they afflicted me.</hi> For this ſeemeth to be not only
an affliction, but an utter Deſolation and Deſtruction. As we privately
feel this every one in our own Hearts and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; ſo the whole body
of the Church in all times doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that it is vehemently aſſailed
with ſtrong and mighty Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of moſt deadly Enemies of all Nations, and
oppugned with the Engines of all Tentations and Tribulations, even from her
youth, that is, from the time that when the People were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of
<hi>Egypt,</hi> they began to be known from other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to be the
people of God.</p>
               <p>But here the Church and the Children of God comfort and raiſe
up themſelves again, having good Experience that in all theſe Calamities
God ſhewed forth his Power, and not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their Sin, but alſo
turned away the puniſhment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo that ſtill they remained a
Church, and the practices of their Enemies were brought to nought. Wherefore
the Prophet here, not only repeateth the danger and calamity of the Church, but
with great joy he addeth withal an Exhortation, that every member of this body
ſhould praiſe the mercy and goodneſs of the Lord, and ſay. <hi>They
could not prevail againſt me.</hi> This is a ſingular Conſolation, not
only for the whole Church of God, but alſo for every one of us particularly,
againſt the proud brags of our Enemies, and the great hope which they have
conceived, that they ſhall prevail againſt us. Hereticks and Sectaries do
glory that they ſhall have the Victory. The Pope vaunting of his own
ſtrength, and the power of Princes, cryeth out; We ſhall overcome. Satan
joyneth with them both, and raiſeth up ſuch troubles, that it ſeemeth
doubtful to whom the victory will fall. This oppreſſeth, not only every man
privately, with great heavineſs and ſorrow, but alſo the whole Church. As
we by Experience did prove in the Aſſembly gathered at <hi>Auguſta,</hi>
where it ſeemed that our Enemies ſhould utterly have ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us up.
But did not we there find theſe words to be full of Conſolation? They could
not prevail. This Conſolation we muſt hold faſt even when we are killed,
as by the Examples of the primitive Church we are taught. For the Church is as
it were watered with the blood of the faithful, that the greater 
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172313:19"/>inccreaſe may come thereof. Now, like as theſe words of
the Prophet are rightly applyed to that perſecution which is done with the
ſword, ſo muſt they be applyed alſo to the aſſaults of Hereticks
and Enthuſiaſts For it is their property to boaſt and brag of the
Conqueſt, and always to triumph before the victory. But how ſoever our
adverſaries triumph and glory, let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to hold faſt the word, and
whatſoever we do, let us ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it wholly to the amplyfying of the Kingdom of
Chriſt and his word. If then (as needs it muſt be) aſſaults and battels
do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, yet let us ſing with <hi>David, They could not prevail.</hi> For
albeit they kill us, yet neither the Pope, nor any other hereticks, nor the
Turk, nor Satan himſelf, ſhall ever be able to quench the Word: Neither yet
ſhall they prevail againſt us if we ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abide in the Word.
Indeed this will we grant unto Satan, that he is ſtronger than we, and vexeth
us many wayes. For many are the troubles of the juſt, but God will deliver
them out of all. And why? Becauſe it is the word of God which they profeſs
and teach; and moreover it is Gods own cauſe which they defend. Wherefore
although the Pope attempt and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe never ſo much miſchief, and go
about to ſtir up the whole world againſt us; although falſe brethren
which walk not in true and ſound doctrine, continually vex us, although Satan
himſelf never ceaſe to raiſe up the gates of hell againſt us, yet will
we ſing with <hi>David</hi> even to the end, <hi>They could not prevail;</hi>
yea and that only becauſe of the word.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 3.</hi> The Plowers plowed upon my back, and they
made long furrows.</head>
               <p>See what unlike and almoſt contrary things he joyneth here
together. Before he comforted the faithfull, that the enemies ſhould never be
able to do any thing againſt the Church, becauſe it is invincible and
cannot be overcome: and here he complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that they plow upon the backs of
the Church, and make ſuch furrow, as ſeem to be of an infinite length. This
is an offence therefore which vehemently troubleth the godly, that God
ſuffereth Satan and the world ſo long to rage, ſo long to vex and afflict
the Church, that he giveth ſucceſs unto their wicked counſels and
attempts; that he ſuffereth the ungodly <pb n="34" facs="tcp:172313:20"/>even then to
proſper when they are moſt worthy to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all manner of
torments, and utterly conſumed. On the othe other ſide, the godly, the more
they pray, and the more they hope, the leſs ſeemeth their prayer and their
hope to take effect: Every day are they more and more afflicted: every day
there is leſs and leſs hope left. Wherefore this ſimilitude is well
applied unto them in that they are compar'd to a ground which is continually
plowed; wherein ſuch furrows are drawn as ſeem to have no end; as though
there were no God which either ſeeth their calamity, or the impiety and
outragious cruelty of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the word. He ſignifieth therefore that
they have need of continual patience, not for a day or two, but all the days of
their life. So that they which have the word, muſt aſſuredly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
and determine, never to depart from God, although they ſhould ſuffer the
ſame afflictions a thouſand years together. How many have we ſeen in
theſe our days which have fallen away, (yea and ſuch alſo as ſometime
did ſtand) when the fruit of the word was hindred through Perſecution, like
as the Sun dryeth up and withereth the Corn that is ſown in a ſtony
ground?</p>
               <p>Wherefore we muſt learn that the patience of the faithful, as
it is in this verſe deſcribed, is ſuch as is ready to offer their backs
unto the Plowers, and to ſuffer not for a day nor for a year, but for the
time of their whole life. For he compareth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions to the long plowing on
the back of the faithful: Like as our Saviour Chriſt alſo ſignifieth,
when he ſaith, <hi>He that continueth to the end ſhall be ſaved.</hi> For
to begin is not enough. And that patience which hath her bounds and limits
preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, may be found even among the Gentiles. But the patience of
Chriſtians is perpetual, that is to ſay, ſuch a patience as ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to
be infinite and without end; for the end thereof doth not appear. Like as on
the other ſide, the end of their conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on appeareth not. So that
thoſe things which ſeem to be moſt contrary, are here joyned together;
that is to ſay, the length and the long continuance of the furrows on the
back of the faithful, and the victory of the faithful, ſinging of thoſe
which drive the Plow, <hi>They could not prevail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Morever, this great and long continuance of the furrows on the
back of the faithful, includeth ſuch an offence as no car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172313:20"/>wiſdom is able to overcome; namely that the wicked do not
only proſper, but their felicity alſo continueth long, ſo that it
ſeemeth to be as a reward of their Tyranny, their perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and malice
againſt the Church. For if God would ſuffer their tyranny but for a little
time, and ſpeedily reward them according to their deſerts, we ſhould all
then ſay that God is mindful of his children, and angry with the wicked. But
now, ſince impiety and Wickedneſs flouriſheth many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and
the wicked ſtill continue and increaſe in great felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without
puniſhment, the ſame is verified of them which <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſaid of
<hi>Harpalus,</hi> That they ſeem to give a lively te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony againſt the
Gods. Yea the godly are ſo vehemently tempted thro' this long continuance,
and fall ſo far, that they think God hath no regard of them. Wherefore we
muſt ſo arm our ſelves with Chriſtian patience, that albeit we feel the
tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and long continuance of theſe furrows, we be not therefore offended,
but when one tentation is overcome, we muſt prepare our ſelves to another.
For our backs muſt be always ready to bear the long continuance of theſe
furrows.</p>
               <p>This is the firſt part of the Pſalm, in the which he
confeſſeth the divine miracles and miraculous power of God, whereby he
preſerveth his children not onely againſt the world, but alſo againſt
Sin, Death and the Devil, and praiſeth God for that he giveth victory to
thoſe that are overcome, and putteth thoſe to flight which do overcome.
This joyful end and this ſucceſs he willeth us to look and wait for, and
exhorteth us to pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Now he turneth himſelf to prayer, and not only
prayeth but alſo promiſeth to the enemies of the Goſpel, that although
they obſtinately continue in afflicting the faithful without check or
puniſhment, yet ſhall their ruine and overthrow be ſuch, that they
ſhall never riſe again; as experience doth ſhew. For I pray you, what
Kingdom from the beginning of the world hath always continued and proſpered?
The places and ſpaces of the earth do remain void and deſolate, and the
Kingdoms are gone as though they had never been. Again, the cruelty and tyranny
of the Kingdoms of the world was never ſo great, that it was able to
oppreſs the Church. For the Church ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth and ſhall continue
to the end of the vvorld, as follvveth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:172313:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 4.</hi> The Righteous Lord hath cut the cords of
the wicked.</head>
               <p>Theſe words are ſo full of conſolation, that to the
children of God in their calamities and afflictions, nothing can be more
comfortable. For they know that no munitions, no furniture of war can be ſo
ſtrong. Firſt of all therefore, weigh and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der why he calleth the
Lord <hi>Righteous,</hi> and ye ſhall ſee that he ſo doth, becauſe
that, when a man conſidereth <hi>according</hi> to the judgment of the
fleſh, the things which are here done, and how God governeth and ruleth the
ſame, it ſeemeth no otherwiſe but that he is unrighteous and unjuſt in
ſupporting the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the wicked with great riches, power, dignity,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> When reaſon ſeeth this, it can judg nothing elſe, but
that if there be a God, he is unjuſt. For firſt of all thus doth reaſon
gather: If there be a God, he is able to reſiſt the wicked, and utterly to
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them. For to be a God is to be Almighty. Again, thus carnal reaſon
argueth: If there be a God, he muſt needs know thoſe things which are done
in the world; for it cannot be ſaid of God, that he is ignorant of any thing.
Now what elſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth hereof, but that if God know theſe things to be
cruelly and unjuſtly done, and he is able to reſiſt them, he ought alſo
to be no leſs willing to do the ſame. For if we think that he will not do
that which he knoweth and is able to do, it muſt follow that he is not good,
but evil; not juſt, but unjuſt. Now lay theſe things together. If God
have power, wiſdom and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in him; if he be able to help; if he know
how, and alſo be willing to help; why are all theſe things done and
governed in the world in ſuch ſort, that the wicked have power, riches
&amp; dignity, as a reward of their impiety? and contrariwiſe the godly for
their piety and godlineſs are many ways and moſt cruelly afflicted? All
theſe things are a lively teſtimony againſt God, as before we ſaid of
<hi>Diogenes.</hi> This argument of <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and ſuch like
Atheiſts, is to the fleſh invincible. Wherefore reaſon being altogether
blinded and wrapped in theſe ſnares, inclineth to this opinion, That there
is no God, or elſe that he regardeth not the affairs of men.</p>
               <p>Of this offence and ſtumbling block the holy Ghoſt warneth
us, when he attributeth this name unto God, that he is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172313:21"/>whom unrighteouſneſs and impiety pleaſeth not.
There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although he ſuffer the wicked to flouriſh for a time, yet at the
laſt he cutteth their cords, that is, he deſtroyeth both their power and
them, according to that ſaying,<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou
art not a God that loveth wickedneſs.</hi> Wherefore let Chriſtians learn
to judge, not by that which preſently they feel, but by that which the Word
of God promiſeth, and ſhall aſſuredly come to paſs; to wit, That the
wicked, when they have long plowed upon the backs of the faithful, and many
ways afflicted them, ſhall periſh at the length. For God is juſt, and his
juſtice will not ſuffer the righteous to be oppreſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 5.</hi> Let them that hate Sion be confounded and
turned back.</head>
               <p>This (as before I have ſaid) is a Prayer. But ye know that in
every Prayer there is a Promiſe included, which Promiſe this word
<hi>Righteous</hi> doth expreſs in the former verſe with a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
vehemency, to the end we ſhould not murmur, or blaſpheme God, as though he
were not mindful of us, or had not regard of us. Now, where he ſaith, <hi>Let
them be confounded and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back;</hi> it is an expoſition of that which
he ſaid before, that their cords ſhould be cut, that is to ſay, their
Kingdoms, their Power, their Riches, their Laws, and finally their whole
poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick body and common weal ſhould be brought to nought: as it befell to
<hi>Babylon, Ninive, Jeruſalem, Athens, Corinth, Thebes, Rome,</hi> and
briefly to all theſe Kingdoms and Common-weales, which did not ſubmit
themſelves to the Goſpel. For when they proudly ſtretched out their necks
and ſet themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt their King, and by their power
ſought to oppreſs him, they were deſtroyed. In like manner muſt we
alſo pray, and certainly look for the execution of Gods vengeance upon
thoſe which at this day have ſet themſelves againſt the Goſpel; as
the Pope and his Biſhops, with all their faction, and with all the Kings and
Princes of the earth which maintain and defend their impiety; for at the laſt
they ſhall be confounded. But the Goſpel and the Word of the Lord ſhall
endure for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. For the name of Chriſt ſhall never be oppreſſed, but
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faithfully called upon, ſhall always be ready to help the afflicted,
and ſhall cut the cords now of the wicked man, and now of that.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:172313:22"/>
               <p>Thus the Holy Ghoſt comforteth us ſundry ways. For when we
have learned that Satan is ſuch a Spirit as never ceaſeth to tempt and to
vex us, (ſo that when he cannot overcome us by the greatneſs and multitude
of tentations, he goeth about to do it by the tediouſneſs and long
continuance thereof) he would have us to comfort our ſelves herewith, that
albeit theſe tentations continue long, yet notwithſtanding they ſhall
have an end. And ſince we are forewarned both of the continuance &amp; of the
end thereof, it is the more eaſy for as to bear them. Here is to be noted
alſo that he ſheweth to whom he wiſheth evil, namely to thoſe which
hate <hi>Sion.</hi> And that hatred which they bare againſt <hi>Sion,</hi>
was an hatred againſt God. For in that Satan hateth the Church, he doth it
not only in reſpect of men, but becauſe he hateth God himſelf, whom the
Church praiſeth and magnifieth. Moreover, <hi>Sion</hi> was a place which God
had choſen unto himſelf. Like as therefore God had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen that place to
ſhew his great love towards it; ſo had Satan choſen the ſame to ſhew
his malice againſt it, and with all his power to vex it. In like manner, not
only Satan, but alſo the malignant Church of the <hi>Pope,</hi> doth
perſecute us; not becauſe we are evil in the ſight of the World; for this
they could well ſuffer, yea and would be glad if they might hear that we are
Whoremongers and Murtherers as they are: But the true cauſe why they ſo
deadly hate and perſecute us, is this, for that it grieveth them, that we in
their eyes are innocent as touching the ſecond table, and alſo obedient to
the firſt; wherein we are commanded to honour, ſerve, and praiſe the
Lord; to fear him, and truſt in his Mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 6.</hi> Let them be as the graſs on the tops of
the houſes, which withereth afore it cometh forth.</head>
               <p>This is a goodly Pſalm, for the ſundry, excellent, and
moſt apt ſimilitudes contained therein, whereby the Holy Ghoſt paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
out thoſe great Majeſties and Principalities of the World, which fight
againſt the the Goſpel. A little before he compared them to plowers drawing
out furrows of a marvellous length; to whom he ſo compareth them, not in this
reſpect, as though it were granted unto them ſo long to abuſe their
power, wealth; <pb n="39" facs="tcp:172313:22"/>and riches; but in reſpect of the great
Tediouſneſs, Grief, and anguiſh of thoſe which ſuffer the Plowers,
the Furrows, the Wounds, and treading under foot; for unto them it ſeemeth a
tedious, a long, and as it were an infinite Plowing. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they deſire
to be delivered, and never ſo little tarrying (through this tediouſneſs
and anguiſh of heart) ſeemeth to them intollerable. Againſt this
Wearineſs and thi, Tediouſneſs therefore, he comforteth the faithful with
this ſimilitude, <hi>of graſs in the top of the houſe.</hi> As if he
ſaid, Why ſeemeth the time ſo long, and tedious unto thee? Why doſt
thou not learn to underſtand what theſe Plowers thy Adverſaries be?
Didſt thou never ſee graſs growing on the tops of houſes? Who did ever
complain that the graſs flouriſhed ſo long? who ever went about to pluck
it up? As though it were not wont of it ſelf to wither and vaniſh away.
Learn therefore that the very ſame is the ſtate and condition of thine
Adverſaries. Thus with one ſimilitude he ſighteth againſt another.<note place="margin">He ſetteth the ſimilitude of the graſs in the houſe top,
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of the Plowers.</note> But if a man could
effectually believe that this ſimilitude was made and here ſet down by the
Holy Ghoſt, and cloſe up the ſame fully in his heart; he ſhould fear
neither the Turk dor the Pope, with all his cruel Prelates, nor the Tyranny of
Princes, but ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn them all, and as little regard them as the
graſs on the tops of the houſes.</p>
               <p>But behold the outward ſhew of this graſs. If any child
ſhould ſee it, he would eſteem it to be better then any Barley, (for to
Barley it is moſt like) ſince it groweth not as other things do upon the
Earth, but in an higher and more notable place, and loadeth the tops of the
houſes. But take a man that knoweth theſe things, and he will ſay it is
nothing elſe but a goodly ſhew and reſemblance without any fruit. Thus
hath the Holy Ghoſt choſen this ſimilitude to teach us, not to wiſh the
Tyrants may be like graſs, but to know that they are indeed moſt like unto
graſs on the houſe tops, which withereth away before the harveſt time
come, or any man go about to cut it down. <hi>Senacherib</hi> who beſieged
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did flie over King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, oppreſſed and trod down all
things under his feet: therefore he could not be counted of <hi>Ezechia</hi>
&amp; others like unto graſs; and yet before he atchieved what he went about,
he was compelled, not without great fear, and alſo much ſlaughter of 
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172313:23"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:172313:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:172313:24"/>his ſouldiers, to raiſe his
ſiege, and he himſelf moſt miſerably periſhed. So <hi>Pharoah</hi>
ſeemed mightily to grow and increaſe, not upon the earth, but in the air
and upon the houſe tops; but the miſerable Jews were oppreſſed and
trodden under foot like mire in the ſtreets. This is a reſemblance of
graſs, not withering but freſhly flouriſhing. But how quickly did it
wither and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh to nothing? For when <hi>Pharoah</hi> did verily think to
oppreſs them, he was ſuddenly oppreſſed himſelf and periſhed in the
waters.</p>
               <p>Such an image of Tyrants and Tyranny the Holy Ghoſt paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
out unto us in this place. Why then ſhouldeſt thou fear? Why ſhouldeſt
thou tremble? Why ſhouldeſt thou deſpair, as though thou hadſt never
ſeen moſt flouriſhing graſs within few days to wither away of its own
accord, or didſt not know the nature of it to be ſuch as cannot long
continue? <hi>Athanaſius</hi> (when <hi>Julianus</hi> the Emperour did many
wayes afflict both him and the whole Church, and fought, not only with cruelty,
but alſo with craft and ſubtilty againſt the faithful, inſomuch that
others, as it were in a terrible tempeſt, were utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and
paſt all hope of deliverance) ſaid that this Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of
<hi>Julian</hi> was not a tempeſt but a little cloud. Indeed his heart was
full of faith which could believe, that <hi>Julianus</hi> was like, not to a
terrible and a violent tempeſt, not to a mighty black cloud wrapping all
things in darkneſs, but unto a very little cloud, which the Sun doth quickly
conſume. In like manner muſt we alſo extenuate and diminiſh the power
of our adverſaries, and ſet at nought all their proud brags, and all their
cruelty; not in reſpect of our own ſtrength, but becauſe they are of
themſelves nothing elſe but a bubble in the water, graſs on the houſe
tops, and a very ſhadow rather then men; beſides this, that they provoke
God alſo againſt themſelves; whoſe fury &amp; cruelty compared unto his
power, is a thing more vain than graſs on the houſe tops, or a bubble in
the water; for it is nothing but a bare and a naked ſhew, which ſeemeth to
be ſomething, when indeed it is nothing. So are all the attempts of the
adverſaries; full of threatnings, but in the end they come to nothing.</p>
               <p>This is the wiſdom of Chriſtians, to diminiſh the power of
the adverſaries, and contrariwiſe to amplifie the Word and 
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172313:24"/>the mighty protection of the Lord. The Devil, Sin, Death,
and other ſpiritual tentations are great; but a Chriſtian can make a
diſtinction of greatneſs. For greatneſs is underſtood two manner of
ways: The one is according to the eye, which the eye judgeth after the outward
ſhew; the other is according to the truth, which the truth judgeth after the
Word. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therefore of Sin, Death, wicked Kings, Princes, and
Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, is that which is according to the eye only: For God which ſaith,
<hi>Be of good comfort, I have overcome the World:</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>Fear not
thoſe which can kill the Body, but are not able to kill the Soul,</hi> the
ſame God alone (I ſay) is the very true greatneſs, to which if you
compare Satan, and all the fury of the whole World, what are they elſe but a
bubble? what are they elſe but graſs? but light ſtraw and ſtubble? But
when they are conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without God, then do they terrify with a falſe
fearful ſhew, and ſeem to be great indeed.</p>
               <p>Wherefore Chriſtians muſt judge, not according to their
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but according to the truth. For an opinion is that which Reaſon
bringeth forth beſides the Word; but Truth is grounded upon the Word, which
judgeth the fury and the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of the World raging againſt the faithful,
to be like unto graſs on the houſe tops. This promiſe being ſetled and
ſurely fixed in the mind,<note place="margin">This Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the enemies
are like graſs, and therefore ſhall periſh, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a
promiſe.</note> confirmeth the godly againſt the great power (as to
reaſon it ſeemeth) of the World and Satan. Like as on the other ſide,
where the word is not, the mind deceived thro' a terrible ſhew of Truth, and
the judgment of Reaſon, is oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with terror. Theſe things muſt
not ſo be taken, as tho' we did utterly condemn the power of Princes, and of
the World, which we count to be the creature of God; but their preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and the abuſe of their power is it that we condemn, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they fight
therewith againſt God and his Church. Let them be Princes on the earth; Let
them uſe their Power and Authority in the World, but when they will needs
make War in Heaven, and with their Power go about to invade and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the
word, this is horrible, this is execrable and damnable. And who ſo compareth
them to bubbles, to graſs, to ſtubble, yea and to nothing, he ſaith
truly, he judgeth rightly. For why do they fight againſt God? Think they that
we know not what <pb n="42" facs="tcp:172313:25"/>God is? and what man is? what the Creature
is, and what the Creator is?</p>
               <p>Wherefore they are rightly compared to graſs on the houſe
tops; for more contemptuouſly the Holy Ghoſt could not ſpeak of them. For
this graſs is ſuch, that it ſoon withereth away before the ſickle be
put unto it. Yea, no man thinketh it worthy to be cut down, no man regardeth
it, every man ſuffereth it to brag for a while, and to ſhew it ſelf unto
men from the houſe tops as though it were ſomewhat when it is nothing. So
the wicked Perſecutors in the World, which are taken to be mighty and
terrible according to the outward ſhew, are of all men moſt contemptible.
For Chriſtians do not once think of plucking them up, or cutting them down;
they perſecute them not, they revenge not their own injuries, but ſuffer
them to increaſe, to brag and glory as much as they liſt; For they know
that they cannot abide the violence of a vehement Wind. Yea though all things
be in quietneſs, yet as graſs on the houſe tops, by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little
withereth away through the heat of the Sun, ſo Tyrants upon ſmall
occaſions do periſh and ſoon vaniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. The faithful therefore in
ſuffering do prevail and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome; but the wicked in doing, are overthrown
and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably periſh, as all the Hiſtories of all times and ages do
plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly witneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 7.</hi> Whereof the Mower filleth not his hand,
neither the Gleaner his Lap.</head>
               <p>Here the Holy Ghoſt maketh a compariſon between Graſs
which yieldeth no fruit, and true corn which is fruitful; that thereby he may
the better commend unto us the former ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and withdraw our minds
from the falſe dread and terror which that vain and counterfeit ſhew
bringeth. Fruitful corn (ſaith he) is ſuch, that he which moweth it ſhall
fill his hand, and he that gathereth the ſheaves ſhall have plenty to carry
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his barn. Here ye ſee, is a truth, and not a vain ſhew. But graſs
on the houſe tops maketh a ſhew of that which is not true, becauſe it is
fruitleſs. So the Pope and his Prelates, with other Tyrants and
Perſecutors, have a reſemblance and a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit ſhew that they are the
Church. They hold and enjoy <pb n="43" facs="tcp:172313:25"/>Dignities, Prebends, Benefices,
as graſs hath his ſtalk and ear; but indeed they are none of the Chrrch,
like as graſs is no Corn: for it withereth away before it can bring forth
fruit.</p>
               <p>For this is the chiefeſt argument wherewith they fight
againſt us, that for this glorious ſhew whereof I ſpeak, they uſurp and
challenge to themſelves the title of the Church. But we are commanded to take
heed that we be not deceived by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhews. Yea and we are admoniſhed
alſo that ſuch ſhews are oftentimes occaſions of great calamities.
<hi>Beware</hi> (ſaith our Saviour Chriſt) <hi>of Falſe Prophets, which
come to you in Sheeps-cloathing.</hi> Alſo <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall
know them.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as then they challenge unto themſelves the name of the
Church, and for a goodly ſhew (which the graſs alſo that groweth on the
houſe tops hath as well as they,) will be counted good Corn: this will not we
grant them. For if they be good Corn, let them fill the hand of the Mower, but
this they do not. They are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Graſs, yea worſe then graſs. For
in that filthineſs of their wicked luſts and fleſhly pleaſures
wherewith they are horribly polluted, and that cruelty which they exerciſe
againſt the true Church, they retain not ſo much as the outward ſhew
which they pretend. Wherefore, ſince there is nothing to be found in our
adverſaries but a naked and an hypocritical ſhew, and the ſame alſo
miſerably and many ways deformed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced; ſince (I ſay) there is
nothing elſe in them but meer hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, we judge and denounce them not to
be the Church of Chriſt, but of Satan. Wherefore they are prepared as chaff
and ſtubble to the fire, although under a ſhevv and colour of the Church,
they afflict and Perſecute us never ſo much.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſe 8.</hi> Neither they which go by ſay, We
bleſs you in the name of the Lord.</head>
               <p>This alſo commendeth and ſetteth forth unto us the
ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the graſs. For true Corn hath this commendation, that it is
the bleſſing of God. They therefore vvhich ſee it grovv, vviſh that God
vvould bleſs and proſper it. This (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) ſhall not be
ſaid of that graſs; that is to ſay, of the Tyrants and the adverſaries
of the Church, but rather they ſhall be curſed <pb n="44" facs="tcp:172313:26"/>of all
men, yea the malediction both of God and man ſhall be heaped upon them: Like
as it hath alſo hapned to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which before our
doctrine and preaching moſt gloriouſly flouriſhed. But now that the
Goſpel hath plucked away her viſour, and ſheweth that ſhe is not
without fruit, all her curſed hypocriſy is bewrayed, and her memory is
periſh'd from among the godly. Thus the Prophet comforteth the faithful, and
ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the wicked (what glorious brag and pretence ſoever they make)
are indeed nothing, and becauſe God bleſſeth them not, they ſhall
inherit nothing but malediction, and ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, like as
<hi>Judas;</hi> the Phariſees, <hi>Corinthus, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius,</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius,</hi> though they
ſeemed to ſlouriſh, moſt miſerably periſhed with all their
glory.</p>
               <p>Wherefore let us, whoſe doctrine by the grace of God is
ſound and agreeable with the holy Scripture, remember this ſimilitude, that
when we muſt ſuffer hatred, ſlander, reproaches and all manner of
injuries for the Goſpels ſake, we are not afraid but may learn hereby to
judge the Pope, the Biſhops, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Princes, with the tormentors and
executioners of their cruelty, to be nothing elſe but graſs on the houſe
tops, which ſeemeth to be ſomewhat, when indeed it is nothing, and
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is without all bleſſing. To ſuch it ſhall be ſaid with
the rich glutton in hell,<note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Son remember
that thou in thy life time receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt thy pleaſures.</hi> For if we
conſider the whole hiſtory of the Church even from the beginning of the
world, we ſhall ſee that God hath always ſo wrought by his ſecret
counſel, that as graſs on the houſe tops withereth away before the
harveſt come: ſo Tyrants are ſuddenly cut off and never come to their
full time. Wherefore let us conſtantly abide and endure with patience in all
afflictions, until the end do ſhew that it was nothing but graſs, and
ſuddenly withered when it was moſt like to increaſe and flouriſh. The
wicked do enjoy all good things for the Churches ſake, like as the graſs on
the houſe tops hath the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the rain and of the Sun as well as the
Corn in the fields. But as they ſhall not live half their days, and as they
ſhall ſee their own counſels and devices to be but vain and without
ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, ſo ſhall they be as a perpetual ſhame among men:
inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that no man ſhall wiſh any good unto them: As at this day the
memory of <hi>Judas, Pilate,</hi> the wicked Jews <hi>Diocleſianus, 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172313:26"/>Maximinus</hi> and other Tyrants, is without honour, yea
moſt execrable and odious unto all men. This conſolation is ſet forth by
the holy Ghoſt by theſe groſs ſimilitudes and examples, that we may
conceive in our minds ſome ſhadow or reſemblance of Gods Works, ſince
we cannot rightly judge and eſteem the things themſelves according to the
truth, but we judge the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Perſecutors of the Church by their
goodly ſhew and outvvard appearance, to be good Wheat, becauſe they
proſper and flouriſh ſo long upon the earth. Wherefore vve muſt reſt
vvholly in the Word, which with ſuch ſimilitudes painteth out theſe
things; and we muſt with draw our ſenſes from all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſights and
ſhews, and judge no otherwiſe of the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the word, then of
moſt vile graſs that groweth on the houſe tops, and is contemned of all
men. For ſo ſaith the Spirit of faith: tho' our ſenſes ſay
otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>In like manner muſt we do alſo in ſpiritual tentations;
when our conſcience accuſeth us and giveth teſtimony againſt us, as
well in the agony and danger of death, as in other conflicts. Here if we follow
that which appeareth to reaſon and our own ſenſes to be true, it ſhall
ſeem unto us that our enemies are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible and almighty, and that there is
no remedy, but we muſt needs be overcome and utterly periſh. The ſight
and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this greatneſs pertaineth to the eyes and to the ſenſes
onely, and riſeth of the judgment of reaſon, and not of the truth. But when
we look to the true greatneſs which the word ſetteth forth unto us, we are
conſtrained to ſay, that Death, Sin, Satan, and the very gates of hell are
indeed nothing elſe but graſs on the houſe tops, but ſtubble, but a
very bubble ſwimming upon the water, vvhich vvith the leaſt occaſion
breaketh and vaniſheth avvay. So muſt theſe things be ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and
ſet againſt all kinds of tentations, vvhether they be Perſecutors of the
Word, as the vvorld and vvicked Princes, or elſe Sin, Death and Satan. All
vvhich vve muſt learn to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate and leſſen as much as vve can,
becauſe Chriſt liveth and vve have his vvord. This conſolation is able to
ſvvallovv up all terrors, and maketh us able to ſay, that all theſe
things are in very deed but one thing. But vvhen vve conſider theſe things
vvithout the Word and Chriſt, in reſpect of our ſelves, and of our ovvn
ſtrength, then are they indeed, not graſs, but ſuch <pb n="46" facs="tcp:172313:27"/>high and mighty mountains as cannot be paſſed over. Where fore
vvhen vve fight againſt our enemies, vve muſt fight, not as men
conſiſting of Body and Soul, but as Chriſtians baptized in the name of
Chriſt, having the gift of the Spirit and the Word. Novv therefore, vvhen the
Devil, Death, Hell it ſelf, the World and Cruel Princes, are compared to a
Chriſtian, they are but graſs upon the houſe tops, or if any thing can be
ſaid to be more vile and contemptible. For he hath the Word, vvhich is
almighty, and moreover he hath Chriſt himſelf. Chriſtians therefore are
invincible,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> yea even then when they are
over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and troden under foot. For the Power of Chriſt is made perfect
through weakneſs. Thus did the holy Prophets and Martyrs comfort themſelves
againſt the World and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Satan, and therefore they did ſo
valiantly ſuffer all kinds of afflictions, being perſvvaded, not that the
graſs, vvhich vvithereth avvay of it ſclf, vvithout mans endeavour, but the
Word of God ſhould have the victory. For true it is that <hi>Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi>
vvriteth vvhen he comforteth the people of <hi>Alexandria</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the
fury of <hi>Arius,</hi> that through the Perſecutions of the Enemies, the
Church doth more and more increaſe and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. Which thing vve alſo have
proved, and God grant that yve and our Poſterity may ſtill ſo do.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="1 Peter 4.11, 5.1-4" type="commentary">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:172313:27"/>
            <head>THE Duty of a Good Shepherd: BY Dr. <hi>MARTIN L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THER:</hi>
Being his COMMENTARY Upon 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3,
4.</head>
            <div n="22" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 PET. 4.11.</hi>
                     </bibl> 
                     <p>If any mnn miniſter, let him do it, as of the ability which
God miniſtreth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WHoſoever executeth any function in the Church, or hath the
cure of Souls committed unto him, may not deal as he liſt himſelf, or to
over-rule matters according to his own ſenſual Will. Neither ſhall he
ſay, Tuſh, I am a Prelate, the people muſt all liſten to that which I
ſay, and obſerve my Laws, Ordinances, and Injunctions without gainſaying.
For God requireth this, that no man miniſter, or do any thing, contrary or
repugnant to that which he commandeth and appointeth. A Prelate or Biſhop (I
ſay) ought to do nothing in the Church, unleſs he be certain and ſure of
the warrantiſe thereof by Gods Word. For God cannot abide to have his
ſervice jumbled and mingled at pleaſure, with every fooliſh Guegaw, and
light trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery. And therefore he ought to have an aſſurance and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
in his mind and Conſcience, that even God both ſpeaketh and worketh in him;
and to ſtand upon ſo ſure a ground for <pb n="48" facs="tcp:172313:28"/>the verity
thereof, that his Faith dare boldly witneſs with him and ſay, Whatſoever
I have ſpoken, and whatſoever I have done, or dealt herein, I am ſo out
of doubt, that the ſame in each reſpect is conſonant to the Word and Will
of God, that I am ready, and dare to ſeal the ſame with my blood, and to
confirm it with my Death. For otherwiſe, if I waver and totter this way and
that way, not knowing whoſe cauſe and buſineſs I have in hand, my Faith
is builded upon the Sand, ſo that the Devil mine Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, is able to
ſhake and tumble it which way he liſt. And therefore we are here
ſtraightly forbidden, not to rely unto, nor to allow whatſoever Decree or
Conſtitution theſe Biſhops liſt to obtrude and enjoyn, unleſs they
ſtand upon a ſure ground, that the things which they do, are allowed of
God, yea done of God himſelf; and unleſs they be able to ſay, Do this,
for it is the Will and Commandment of God, and we have his expreſs Word and
Commandment for our Warrant; If they be not able to ſay thus, they ought to
be accounted as Lyars and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers; much leſs ought any Chriſtian to
yield unto them therein any Obedience or Subſcription. For, the Lord hath
ſo appointed, that our Conſciences ſhould not elſewhere be ſtayed,
but upon the moſt ſure and infallible Rock. And thus much for publick
functions, wherein it is not lawful for us at any hand, to follow our own
wilful Devices, and ſenſual Conceipts; nor to preſcribe any rule or order
to be embraced, unleſs we be undoubtedly aſſured, that it ſtandeth with
the Will and Word of God. Wherein we evidently ſee, how clean againſt the
King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the <hi>Pope,</hi> &amp; his mitred Biſhops (as things therein
are now handled) Saint <hi>Peters</hi> mind and Judgment was, long before any
<hi>Popes</hi> were known in the World, to rule the roſte in ſuch
Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficality, as ſince they have done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1-4" type="verses">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 PET. V. 1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
                     </bibl> 
                     <p>
                        <hi>1.</hi> The Elders which are among you I beſeech, which
am alſo an El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and a witneſs of the ſufferings of Chriſt.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HEre Saint <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth thoſe that have any charge
of feeding the Flock of Chriſt, how they ought to behave themſelves. In the
Chapter afore, he told that none ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume <pb n="49" facs="tcp:172313:28"/>to
teach or preach any thing, unleſs he were certain and aſſured that the
ſame was the ſincere and pure Word of God, upon which as upon a firm and
ſtrong Rock, our Conſciences may boldly ſtay. For this in Duty is
required of us Chriſtians, that we ſhould be certain and know throughly
what thing is allowed of Chriſt, and what is not: for they that waver in
uncertainty of this knowledge, are not to be taken as Chriſtians. He addeth
alſo thus much, that whoſoever entreth into any Office or Function,
ſhould ſo behave himſelf therein, in each reſpect, as that he ſhould
not doubt but that God was the Author thereof. But what he here ſaith,
peculiarly belongeth to Biſhops and Eccleſiaſtical Paſtors, wherein he
teacheth them how they are to demean themſelves in the Adminiſtration of
their duties and charges, and what manner of perſons they ought to be.</p>
               <p>We muſt here further be acquainted with the Phraſe and
Propriety of the Tongue, wherein this Epiſtle was written, that we be not
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived through ignorance of the ſignification and force of the Word. For
this Greek name <hi>Presbuteros,</hi> which St. <hi>Peter</hi> here uſeth,
doth ſignfiy <hi>An Elder:</hi> by which Word they alſo are called that be
Senators; that is, men excelling in Age, Gravity, Vertue, Wiſdom, and
Experience. After the ſame ſort, doth Chriſt call his Diſciples,
Miniſters, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, to whoſe Office it belongeth to overſee and
govern his ſpiritual Empire (that is, to preach and to take care of the
Chriſtian Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation) by the name of <hi>Elders.</hi> And therefore
marvail not a whit, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let any thing move thee, though they which be
<hi>Elders,</hi> be now a days called by other Titles or Names, whereof the
Scripture maketh no mention at all; But not reſpecting the order, wherein
things preſently ſtand, weigh and conceive the matter thus: When St.
<hi>Peter</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Apoſtles, came into any City wherein
Chriſtians were, they ordained ſome one or other of them, ſuch as lived
honeſtly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable, and had Wife and Children, and alſo skilful in
the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, to have the Superintendency and charge over the reſt.
And them they called Seniors or Elders, whom afterward both St.
<hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> called Biſhops, whereby we may
note, that <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> were no other, then the very ſame that were
<hi>Elders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching this purpoſe, we read in the Hiſtory of St.
<hi>Martin,</hi> how a certain man came unto a place in <hi>Africa,</hi> and
there in a poor Cottage found an Elderly man, whom they thought to have been
ſome plain Country-man. Within a while, they ſaw many people come flocking
to him, to whom he Preached and Expounded the Word of God, whereby they
perceived that he was their Paſtor or Biſhop. For in thoſe days, 
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172313:29"/>there was no difference either in Apparel or manners
between the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and reſidue of Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Elders</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>upon whom
the charge lyeth, to feed the flock of Chriſt with the Word of God, and to
have care over them in the Lord, I exhort, which am alſo an Elder.</hi>
Whereby it manifeſtly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that they whom he here nameth
<hi>Elders,</hi> were ſuch as laboured in the Miniſtry of the Word, and
diligently preached the glad Tydings of the Goſpel. For, ſuch as he was
that calleth himſelf their fellow Elder, ſuch alſo appeareth it that they
were. And here we ſee, how far he humbleth and abaſeth himſelf, in that,
he taketh not upon him the name of a Prelate, (which in reſpect that he was
an Apoſtle of the Lord he might have done) but calleth himſelf a <hi>Fellow
Elder, and alſo a witneſs of the Sufferings of Chriſt.</hi> As if he had
ſaid, <hi>I do not only preach, but I am alſo among thoſe Confeſſors
of Chriſt, that are exerciſed in dayly Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</hi> And withal he
alſo ſheweth that ſo many as be Chriſtians, muſt be perſecuted and
ſuffer affliction. And this is a true Apoſtle of Chriſt, unto whom if the
<hi>Pope</hi> and his Biſhops were any thing like, (as they are ſhameleſs
enough, to challenge to themſelves the ſame Title) we would not greatly
ſtick, willingly to kiſs their feet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſ. 1.</hi> And alſo a Partaker of the Glory that
ſhall be Revealed.</head>
               <p>This part of the Apoſtles Style and Title, is of far more
excellency, then any that our <hi>Popiſh</hi> Biſhops dare pretend to
uſe. For thereby doth St. <hi>Peter</hi> take and reckon himſelf Holy, and
a bleſſed Man. And altho' he perfectly knew, that he ſhould be a Partaker
of the Glory to come, yet taketh he no Pride therein, he lifteth not himſelf
up in any ſwelling Glory, but modeſtly containeth himſelf within the
bounds of temperate ſoftneſs and courteſy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>V. 2.</hi> Feed the flock of God, which dependeth upon
you, caring for it, not by conſtraint, but willingly; not for filthy Lucre,
but of a ready Mind.</head>
               <p>Chriſt is the firſt and chiefeſt Paſtour, who hath many
Paſtours under him; as he alſo hath many Flocks: whom being diſperſed
in ſundry quarters of the World, he committeth to the charge and overſight
of their Shepherds and Paſtours, as in this Epiſtle of St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
written in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to divers Countries and Regions, appeareth. But what is the charge
of theſe Paſtours to do? Forſooth, to <hi>feed the Flock of
Chriſt.</hi> This word <hi>(Feed)</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> hath raked and haled
unto himſelf, whereby he goeth <pb n="51" facs="tcp:172313:29"/>about to prove himſelf
Lord and Prince of all, and that it is in our own choice and Authority, to deal
with the Sheep as he liſteth himſelf. But alas, who is ſo ignorant that
knoweth not what this word (Feed) meaneth: To wit, that the Paſtours and
Shepherds ought to provide Paſture for their Sheep, and to ſee them have
their meat in convenient and due ſeaſon, whereby they may grow to be
fruitful: And moreover to watch that <hi>devouring Wolves ruſh not in among
them, and tear the Flock in pieces?</hi> This word <hi>(Feed)</hi>
ſigniſieth nothing leſs then to <hi>kill</hi> and <hi>ſpoil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Furthermore St. <hi>Peter</hi> calleth it peculiarly <hi>the
Flock of Chriſt,</hi> as tho' he ſhould ſay, Think not that the Flock is
any of your own, ye are but only Servants and Miniſters to look unto it, ye
are no Lords nor Maſters over it. Contrary to the bold practice and
cuſtomable dealing of many Biſhops, which account and call every one within
their Dioceſs and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, their Sheep. We are the Sheep of Chriſt,
for he ſaid afore, <hi>Ye are now returned unto the Shepherd and Biſhop of
your Souls.</hi> Biſhops are the Miniſters of Chriſt, to keep his Sheep,
and to give them meat and paſture. And therefore to <hi>Feed,</hi> is nothing
elſe then to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, wherewith their Souls may be fed, fatted
and fructified, that ſo the Sheep may be nouriſhed with the Goſpel. This
is the only and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Office of a Biſhop.</p>
               <p>So ſaid Chriſt unto <hi>Peter; Feed my Sheep, Joh.</hi> 21.
that is, the Sheep which I commit unto thee to feed, are not <hi>thine</hi> but
<hi>mine.</hi> Howbeit theſe words have been ſo canvaſſed and wreſted
by my Lord the <hi>Pope,</hi> that he thereby uſurpeth and exerciſeth an
external Domination and Lordſhip over the Church of Chriſt, whereas neither
he, nor any of his ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chaplains, preacheth ſo much as one word
of the Goſpel. They brag that they have their Succeſſion from St.
<hi>Peter.</hi> If it were ſo, yet ſear I, that it could ſcarcely be
proved that any <hi>Pope</hi> ever preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; for none of them
hath left any thing behind him, that is written and extant, wherein a man may
read the Goſpel. St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> was ſurely an holy
man; and yet the things which he preached, are not to be eſteemed worth a
ſtraw; whereby it may appear, that the ſame See of <hi>Rome</hi> is
peculiarly and ſpecially accurſed of God. I deny not, but ſundry of the
<hi>Popes</hi> ſuffered Martyrdom under cruel Tyrants, for the
Goſpels-ſake, but yet there is nothing extant that was written by any of
them, which is Evangelical. And yet they ſtill brag and crack, that it is
their charge to feed, whereas indeed they do nothing elſe but entangle, and
clogge mens Conſciences with Laws of their own, and <pb n="52" facs="tcp:172313:30"/>make
havock and ſale of mens Souls, never troubling themſelves with preaching
one word of Chriſt his ſacred Goſpel.</p>
               <p>True it is, that there are many to be found, as well Women as
men, which are able to preach, and that with no leſs Dexterity and
ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, then he unto whom that charge and office is peculiarly
committed. But becauſe the greateſt number in the flock always is of
weaklings, therefore it is expedient that ſome be appointed to ſtrengthen
and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm ſuch, and to keep back the Wolf from ruſhing in among them,
and devouring them. For a Preachers Office and Duty is not only to feed, that
is, to teach his Sheep, how they ought to frame themſelves to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come true
and ſincere Chriſtians; but he hath the charge alſo to look that the Wolf
be kept out, and that none of the Sheep be devoured, or ſeduced by falſe
Doctrine, and ſo drawn into error, which is the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual drift and practice
of the Devil. Now, there be many that can well enough abide to have the
Goſpel preached, ſo that there might be no exclaiming, and ſpeaking
againſt Wolves; I mean, ſo that Preachers in their Sermons, would forbear
railing and taunting againſt Prelates. But although I preach ſound
Doctrine, and that which is true; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I feed and teach (my charge)
the Sheep, well and rightly; yet is not that ſufficient; for it is further
required at my hands, to keep the Sheep from danger, and to have a careful
regard unto them, that Wolves come not among them, to drive them away out of
their fertile and wholeſome paſtures. For to what purpoſe is my building,
if when I have couched and orderly laid my Stones, another ſtraitways come
and throw them down as faſt again, and I ſeeing him, forbid him not? The
Wolf is well enough contented, that the Sheep be well fed, and fatted in good
paſture; becauſe the fatter they be, the pleaſanter and daintier Prey
thinketh he to make of them. But that Dogs ſhould inceſſantly bark and
baule at him, that can he not abide. And therefore it is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of no
ſmall weight and charge, to feed well, according as God hath given in
Commandment to do; and it behooveth each one in that fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction carefully to
conſider his charge in this behalf.</p>
               <p>The Flock (ſaith he) <hi>which dependeth upon you,</hi> that
is, over which ye have charge, or which is among you, and not which is
ſubject and lying at your feet. <hi>Care for it, and that not by
conſtraint, becauſe you can no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe chooſe, but willingly; not
for filthy lucre ſake, but of a ready mind.</hi> Here he comprehendeth in one
word, all that which the Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiel</hi> in the 34th Chapter of his
Propheſy, writeth concerning Paſtors or Biſhops. The meaning of this
place is thus: Not only feed ye, but take ye care alſo and provide for them,
that they want nothing, and <pb n="53" facs="tcp:172313:30"/>where any ſtandeth in
neceſſity or need, there ſee that ye releive them: and in each reſpect,
do the parts and duties of right <hi>Epiſcopoi,</hi> that good Watchmen and
faithful Eſpials. Look out, leaſt danger appear, ſtand always preſt and
ready on your guard, and diligently behold and eſpy out of your Watch Tower,
what it is that is wanting, or what is befallen unto every one within your
charges. Hereby we may well perceive and know, that a Biſhop is even the
ſame which is here meant by an <hi>Elder.</hi> And therefore it is not true,
which ſome ſay, that a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick is a Dignity, and a Biſhop only he
that weareth a forked Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre. <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is not a name of Dignity,
but of Office: for he that is inveſted with that name and title, ought to
look to his Flock, and to be careful for it, and to ſerve as a good Watchman,
to ſee abroad, and learn what things be amiſs any where within his charge.
As if there be any that is weak, having his conſcience wounded, him ought he
to confirm, comfort and heal: if any fall, him ought he to lift up again, and
ſo as other defects ariſe, to be ready to help, whereby Chriſtian-people
may be ſafficiently looked unto and provided for, both in Soul and in Body.
This is the reaſon that hath moved me therefore oftentimes to ſay, that if
we would inſtitute a right Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, it were neceſſary,
that in every City there ſhould be three or four Superintendents, to take
care and regard over the Church and Congregation, and to reform and reſtore
whatſoever therein is amiſs or wanting.</p>
               <p>And here he toucheth two ſpecial Points, enough almoſt to
terrify and diſcourage any man from bearing Authority over the people, or to
take this great charge and burden upon him. Firſt there be ſome vertuous
and honeſt men, who half unwillingly are drawn into the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry and
function of Preaching; for that, they ſee it to be a painful and laborious
Office, to skout about every where, to ſee how the Sheep live, to ſuccour
and help them that be in want, to ſtrengthen and raiſe up them that be
wavering and ready to fall; and finally to have ſuch diligent care and
continual watch over them, that the Wolf find no entrance to invade and come
ruſhing in among them; yea in that, he muſt not ſtick to lay down his
life for their preſervation and ſafeguard, And alſo for that it is ſuch
an hard matter of ſo great difficulty, truly to diſcharge the office of a
goodly Paſtor: yea of ſo great danger it muſt be throughly executed, and
that not unwillingly, or as though it alſo, becauſe were by conſtraint.
True it is, that no man ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude himſelf into that Office; but if he
be thereunto called an required, he ought willingly to take it upon him, and to
diſcharge and perform as much as to his function and office appertaineth.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:172313:31"/>
               <p>For they that take this matter upon them upon neceſſity and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and have neither courage nor pleaſure in the ſame, ſhall
never with any profit fruitfully diſcharge or execute their office.</p>
               <p>Again, there be others worſe then theſe, which take this
Office upon them for no other end but for filthy Lucre, to ſcrape and rake
together wealth, and to pamper and cram their bellies. Theſe fellows ſeek
only for the Wool and the Milk of the Sheep, but as for good Paſtures for
them they care not; and with this Scab is the Popiſh Clergy horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
infected. And this is a moſt hurtful, dangerous noyſome and filthy Vice,
then which there cannot be any ſo diſhonourable or ſhameful for him that
taketh on him the name and charge of a Chriſtian Biſhop or Paſtor. Which
was the thing that cauſed both the Apoſtles, <hi>Petor</hi> and
<hi>Paul,</hi> and alſo the Prophets, ſo oft to record and inculcate it.
This cauſed <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſay, Numb. 16. <hi>I have not taken ſo
much as an Aſs from them; neither have I hurt any of them.</hi> And
<hi>Samuel</hi> alſo; <hi>Ye know that I have not taken any mans Ox, or Aſs
from him, nor done wrong to any, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. For if he
that hath this charge and function of feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Flock, be greedily given to
ſcraping together of riches and wealth, and to gape after filthy Lucre;
ſuch an one (I ſay) is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf eaſily and ſoon changed from a
Paſtor into a Wolf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſ. 2.</hi> But of a ready mind.</head>
               <p>That is, even with pleaſure. Let the Paſtor or Biſhop
apply his Office and Vocation, and that with a ready willingneſs. They that
thus chearfully, promptly and zealouſly diſcharge their function, are
thoſe, which as they do their duties willingly, ſo do they not greedily
pull the fleece from the Sheep. There be therefore two ſorts of falſe
Paſtors. The one ſort occupy their room grudgingly and unwillingly; the
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther willingly and gladly; but yet for gain and filthy Lucre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſ. 3.</hi> Not as though yo were Lords over Gods
heritage.</head>
               <p>Sueh are they that are willing to take the office upon them, for
dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſake, becauſe they would live pompouſly and bear great ſway
and authority in the World. He therefore exhorteth Biſhops, Eiders and
Paſtors, that they practiſe not any Lordly Tyranny over the Flock, as
though the people were their Slaves and Underlings, or as though they had
ſuch authority and Lordſhip over them, to command what they liſt. For we
have but one Lord, which is Chriſt; and he it is <pb n="55" facs="tcp:172313:31"/>which
governeth our Souls. Elders and Paſtors have no further charge then to feed.
And here in one word, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> utterly overthroweth all the
Ringdoms of the <hi>Pope;</hi> and concludeth that no Biſhop hath any
authority, ſo much as in one word to clog and tye the conſcience of the
faithful to the obſervation of their Precepts. For they themſelves ought to
be Servants and Miniſters, and to ſay, Thus ſaith the Lord, and theſe
be the words of Chriſt; it is not we, the words are none of ours; and
therefore ye ought to do that which is here commanded. According to that which
Chriſt ſaith; <hi>Luke</hi> 32. <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles reign over
them, and they that bear rule over them, are called gracious Lords, but ye
ſhall not be ſo.</hi> Contrary whereunto the Pope boaſteth and braggeth
ſaying, We ought to be Lords, and to us only belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to exerciſe chief
Rule and Supream Authority.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3, 4" type="verse">
               <head>
                  <hi>Verſ. 3.</hi> But that ye may be enſamples to the
Flock. <hi>Verſ. 4.</hi> And when the chief Shepheard ſhall appear, ye
ſhall receive an incorruptible Crown of Glory.</head>
               <p>See that ye be the formoſt in the battle, uſing ſuch
honeſt converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that your life may be a Lanthorn to give light, and
an example to the people, to imitate you. But our Lord <hi>Shaveliugs</hi>
uſe to tell the people another tale, bidding them to do this and that, they
themſelves in the mean while leaning on their ſoft Cuſhions, and taking
their eaſe like Lordings; laying upon us great and grievous burdens, which
they themſelves will not touch nor lift at with one of their fingers; not
travelling any whit in Preaching the true Word of God, but rather commanding
others to do that, which they themſelves never did, nor ever meant to do. And
yet muſt no man tell them thereof, for if he do, he ſhould be ſure
quickly to feel the ſmart of it.</p>
               <p>Again, to ſuch Paſtors Biſhops, Elders and
Superintendents, as here in this world did their duties faithully, truly,
ſincerely, and holily; Saint <hi>Peter</hi> aſſigneth no temporal reward;
as though he ſhould ſay, your Office and Function is of more excellency and
dignity, then that in this life it can be requited and recompenced; there is
due and kept for you an Evelarſting Crown, that ſhall be given unto you
which faithfully and diligently feed the Flock of Chriſt. And this is the
exhortation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Saint <hi>Peter</hi> encourageth them, to whom the
charge and cure of Souls is committed. Whereby is manifeſtly concluded and
proved, that the Pope with his Cardinals and Biſhops is the very
Antichriſt, and <pb n="56" facs="tcp:172313:32"/>and the profeſſed Adverſaries of
Chriſt, for that they do nothing of all theſe, which Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
here requireth. For they neither teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, neither do they any thing
themſelves, but are wholly and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in thoſe devices and by-matters,
which are moſt oppoſite and contrary thereunto. They neither feed the Sheep
themſelves, neither will they ſuffer others to feed them; but rather place
the ravening Wolves, devouring and murthering the Flock, and yet brag they,
that they be Chriſts Vicar on Earth. Too truly (the more pity) are they in
the room and ſtead of Chriſt, being abſent, after the manner and example
of the Devil: For whereſoever Chriſt is not in place, there they bear
ſway, and as Butcherly Tyrants raign and command moſt imperiouſly.</p>
               <p>It is therefore very expedient and requiſite, that the Laity
and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler ſort ſhould perfectly remember this and ſuch like places;
by the which they may be able to anſwer againſt that Antichriſtian
Kingdom of the Pope, whenſoever they ſhall be called into queſtion and
exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as touching their Faith; yea, thus may they well ſay, when they
are brought unto ſuch pinches. Behold Chriſt ſaith thus, and the Pope
ſaith the clean contrary. Chriſt ſaith yea, the Pope ſaith nay. They
therefore thus teaching contrary and repugnant doctrines, the one of them
muſt needs lye. Now, that Chriſt ſhould lye, it is impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſible, and
therefore it is the Pope, that is the lying Ruffian of the world, and not only
a Devilliſh Lyar, but even Antichriſt himſelf. Thus oughteſt thou to be
furniſhed armed with the Scriptures, by the which thou mayſt not only
boldly call the Pope Anticriſt, but mayſt alſo (when thou haſt ſo
done) moſt plainly and eaſily prove it, ſo that thou mayſt ſurely by
the Word of God perſiſt in thine opinion, even to the death, againſt the
Devil and all his Infernal Army.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
